<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dh-Racing on sad spiders</title>
    <link>https://sadspiders.ca/blog/dh-racing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dh-Racing on sad spiders</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-CA</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2022-2025, the spiders.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 08:35:17 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sadspiders.ca/blog/dh-racing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Gravel season returns, set your goals</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/gravel-season-returns-set-your-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 08:35:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/gravel-season-returns-set-your-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summers-almost-over&#34;&gt;SUMMER&amp;rsquo;S ALMOST OVER!!!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As August draws to a close, let&amp;rsquo;s all take a moment to remind it that we all hate it and it&amp;rsquo;s a shitty month and it can fuck off. And take February with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;set-your-goals&#34;&gt;Set Your Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, August is almost over and I haven&amp;rsquo;t got out mountain biking nearly as much as I would have liked, but that&amp;rsquo;s okay. A lot of life has been happening, and we deal with it a day at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spring, you will recall that I finally accomplished my goal of &lt;a href=&#34;../the-windiest-135km-bike-ride/&#34;&gt;doing the 100km+ ride&lt;/a&gt; from our home to my gfs family&amp;rsquo;s farm for Easter. This was my first ride to cross the 100km mark and the conditions were sub-optimal. The windiest day of the year so far as a crosswind definitely didn&amp;rsquo;t make that ride any easier and I was not in the greatest spirits as we crossed the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the obvious thing to do is to create a new, more ambitious goal. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myself and my bicycle, Grimey, will hereby attempt to complete an &amp;ldquo;imperial century&amp;rdquo; ride of 100 miles or more by the end of October of this year. We begin at Buckingham Palace and the Queen herself will drop the green flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I will be renaming our house Buckingham Palace for the occasion and Ashley will be happy to accept the Queen monicker until the mutinies start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;that-sounds-awful&#34;&gt;That sounds awful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s funny because we all keep up with our own version of the Joneses. My youtube feed is full of 150 or more mile ultra-endurance races, so doing a ride like this seems quite tame in comparison. But I mention it to normies (aka friends and family) and they are quick to point out that how do you do that it&amp;rsquo;s so far? Same way as you eat an elephant I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;making-a-plan&#34;&gt;Making a plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this ride will be in less than two months, and possibly within a month or so. Which does not leave a heap of time for training and conditioning. Shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll create a more formal plan for myself, but in the meantime, how to prepare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend more time on the bike. Just in general. Get the body used to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hill training. Head out for less than an hour and repeatedly ride up the biggest hills in the area at full gas, recover on the way back down. It&amp;rsquo;s high-intensity intervals and it sucks but it will build some strength and should hopefully provide quick/substantial cardiovascular gains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longer, mellow rides. Head out to the rail trails and just cruise for two hours or more. Sometimes go for a second ride that day, make sure the body is okay with having to go when it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really want to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eat and ride. When you&amp;rsquo;re out for extended rides and want to make good time, you need to train your body to expend energy and digest at the same time. So bring a substantial snack to eat at the start of the ride, or even at the halfway point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the last ride, my guts felt gross in the second half from eating the [high-calories == crap] food, so I might need to experiment with this a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stay-tuned&#34;&gt;Stay tuned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last ride clocked in around 135km and lasted about seven hours, I think? So planning to tack on another hour, which hopefully won&amp;rsquo;t destroy me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone want to loan me a drone and wants to come out for a small section to get some aerial shots, that&amp;rsquo;d be awesome. No pay!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll keep you posted as we move towards R-day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Project: DH Bike Plates</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 08:30:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction---problem-description&#34;&gt;Introduction - Problem Description&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As everyone who knows me knows, it is not often that you can get through a conversation with me without having bikes come up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since I am a lot lazier than people like to think, I would rather watch biking than participate. So every year I make sure to follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uci.org/calendar/mtb/1voMyukVGR4iZMhMlDfRv0?discipline=MTB&#34;&gt;UCI Downhill Mountain Bike World Cup&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Union Cycliste Internationale&lt;/em&gt;) and watch all of the races lives where possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the run-up to each event, a number of media outlets provide video of practice runs to get an idea of what the track is looking like and how various riders are tackling the difficult sections of track. Althought I very much appreciate what they do, it irks me a bit that they don&amp;rsquo;t include each rider&amp;rsquo;s name on screen to know whom&amp;rsquo;s who. Further complicating things, the plate number for each rider changes &lt;em&gt;every single stupid race&lt;/em&gt;, which means you can&amp;rsquo;t even just memorize plate  numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-solution&#34;&gt;My solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the plate number is based on the riders&amp;rsquo; current UCI ranking, I&amp;rsquo;m going to take the information from UCI&amp;rsquo;s website and add it to a database using &lt;a href=&#34;https://planetscale.com&#34;&gt;Planetscale&lt;/a&gt; and their generous free tier to see hwow things go. I want to add Prisma as on ORM because I like using Prisma as an ORM. I&amp;rsquo;ll start out by simply creating a backend API using TypeScript and &lt;a href=&#34;http://expressjs.com&#34;&gt;Express&lt;/a&gt;. It will start out being &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; bare-bones, since I want this up and running by mid-week in it&amp;rsquo;s most basic form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I have the backend up, I will write a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; simple front-end, probably using Svelte (and Tailwind for prettification) to consume the API. Since this is going to be primarily a mobile app so I can use it while plopped in front of the TV, I have grand plans of using a touch-based quick-scroll mechanism, I&amp;rsquo;ll see how easy that will be to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short term, I may just have to print the information on-screen and have a font-size adjuster so we can get the information as quickly available as possible. This is required because there is no real pattern in the footage being shown in these videos &amp;ndash; you may need to jump from plate 35 of the Elite Women to plate 87 for Elite Men to plate 1 of the Junior Men, so an intuitive interface will be required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;downsides&#34;&gt;Downsides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really want to write a project using Test-Driven Development (TDD). Unfortunately, I want this done &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt; so it won&amp;rsquo;t happen right yet. However, I may continue this project into the winter which could allow for TDD of future functionality. My time limit and &amp;ldquo;would rather have it work than work well&amp;rdquo; attitude wil preclude &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; unit testing during the initial roll-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; set up dummy data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; set up basic API with Express&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; set up Planetscale DB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; write Prisma schema and sync with DB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; verify API works as expected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; make entire front-end first?!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;deadline&#34;&gt;Deadline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a race this week, meaning footage should start rolling out in about two or three days. I want to have &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in place and working by then. Even if it&amp;rsquo;s just a big list of all the riders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best case:&lt;/strong&gt;



























&lt;img 
  sizes=&#34;(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw&#34;
  srcset=&#39;https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/best-case_hu4972109061168556998.jpg 500w, https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/best-case_hu4011339289667783077.jpg 800w, https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/best-case_hu6747575091073472814.jpg 1200w&#39;
  
    src=&#34;https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/best-case.jpg&#34; 
  
  alt=&#34;Stylish rider jumping between two trees&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worst case:&lt;/strong&gt;



























&lt;img 
  sizes=&#34;(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw&#34;
  srcset=&#39;https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/worst-case_hu5510906766473660246.jpg 500w, https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/worst-case_hu8367088164697626681.jpg 800w, https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/worst-case_hu765702448599650213.jpg 1200w&#39;
  
    src=&#34;https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/worst-case.jpg&#34; 
  
  alt=&#34;Rider on their back after a crash with their bike airborne beside them&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the flipside, there&amp;rsquo;s a race next weekend! I encourage everyone to get on board, it&amp;rsquo;s exciting to watch!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Cup Downhill 2022 starts next weekend!</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/world-cup-downhill-2022-starts-next-weekend/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 16:29:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/world-cup-downhill-2022-starts-next-weekend/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;code-orange-all-hands-on-deck&#34;&gt;Code Orange; All hands on deck.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World Cup Downhill racing starts again for the 2022 season this weekend! And yes, you should absolutely watch it. Look, the good nerds over at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redbull.com/int-en/need-to-know-lourdes-uci-mtb-world-cup-preview&#34;&gt;Red Bull&lt;/a&gt; have thrown together a cheat sheet so that you can ignore everything I am about to say and just go there! No wait, do not go to a different website. This is your home now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only race day is a good time, the entire week before the race has daily updates from various athletes and teams released via [&lt;em&gt;popular streaming service&lt;/em&gt;]. If you want to get involved properly, here&amp;rsquo;s a breakdown of some of the best stuff to watch before [&lt;em&gt;streaming service&lt;/em&gt;] learns your preferences and feeds you nothing but this and also weird conspiracy videos because you watched one as a joke once. The only real &amp;ldquo;conspiracy&amp;rdquo; is that Birds aren&amp;rsquo;t Real. Look into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sport attracts a fun array of people. You might think that they are all screw-loose low-IQ weirdos but you would only be one-third right; most of them seem to be of average IQ or higher and generally pretty normal. Getting to know the riders goes a long way in the enjoyment because there will always be people you want to win and people you want to lose. But you have to pretend to be sportsmanlike and just say things like &amp;ldquo;I just want him to win less&amp;rdquo; but it&amp;rsquo;s okay we all do that and know what you mean (&amp;ldquo;fuck that guy&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;track-walk&#34;&gt;Track Walk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before being allowed to ride down the track, all athletes participate in a track walk. This allows them to hang out with one another, tell stories, and if it&amp;rsquo;s been raining they will slip and fall a few times each. I know this because New Zealand native Wyn Masters posts his usually-pretty-good &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iQSVBatQqQY&#34;&gt;WynTV track walks&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: link is from the last time the race was in Lourdes back in 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a great way to learn the players in the game. Wyn is a master interviewer in that he just says whatever he thinks without thinking about it so you learn some fun stuff from everyone. He also seems to be pretty universally liked so everyone is open with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Track walks are also where you can learn which parts of the course riders are excited for and which are dreaded which helps to understand what they&amp;rsquo;re going through come race day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice-videos&#34;&gt;Practice videos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire time after track walk until race day, the good folks down at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vitalmtb.com/&#34;&gt;Vital MTB&lt;/a&gt; release daily footage of what has been happening. These offer good insight into how riders progress from a first attempt at a difficult section to really having it nailed down. There are also usually a fair number of entertaining crashes and occasionally some gnarly/scary-looking crashes. Along with these videos, riders will post their point-of-view footage from practice so you get a vague sense of what things will be like from their perspective. I have a feeling this might actually be better with in virtual reality, since current footage is notoriously bad at conveying how steep things actually are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course I would be remiss not to mention &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pinkbike.com&#34;&gt;Pinkbike&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s coverage in this discussion. They were recently acquired by Outside Media or something and the whole comments section hates them for it, but the comments section is also just notoriously bitchy about everything (e.g. &amp;ldquo;pick a tire size and be a dick about it&amp;rdquo;). Oh yeah, but I was going to say that Pinkbike is also where a lot of these videos are aggregated, so a daily visit to their site for the week before a race will keep you up-to-date on the haps. Also be sure to read the comments because there are a lot of gems scattered in there. Actually, as much as possible, just read the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;qualies-qualifying&#34;&gt;Qualies (Qualifying)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before the race (sometimes two days before) there is a qualifying heat to determine the order everyone will come down the mountain. Red Bull always tries to do this thing where they talk to everyone as soon as their run is done and they are exhausted and can&amp;rsquo;t formulate a decent thought/sentence and it generally sucks shit. It is considered wise to assume that the outcome of qualifying will be almost exactly the same as the outcome of the race because some people do that and others are sarcastic jerks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;race-day-omfg-&#34;&gt;RACE DAY OMFG 🚴💨&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of these races are held in Europe. This weekend, for example, takes places in Lourdes in the French Pyrenees. Neat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The women race first and are definitely entertaining enough to watch. Over the last few years the competition has really upped their game and to win the race they need to hit all the jumps the men do. The &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redbull.com/int-en/events/uci-mountain-bike-world-cup-lourdes&#34;&gt;Red Bull World Cup Downhill brought to you by Mercedez-Benz&lt;/a&gt; (seriously) livestream starts at 6:25am in my part of North America, which means I get to wake up, put on some coffee and spend half my day just relaxing and enjoying some biking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The men&amp;rsquo;s broadbast starts some time around 9:30 or 10 am, about half an hour after the ladies finish and goes for a good while. It usually gets really exciting once the last twenty or so dudes start making their way down. A lot of them are buddies so you&amp;rsquo;ll see some good sportsmanship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rob-warner&#34;&gt;Rob Warner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the announcers is named Rob Warner and even if you don&amp;rsquo;t know what&amp;rsquo;s going on, make sure you have the volume turned up because you&amp;rsquo;ll get really excited just because he gets so damn excited. Seriously, he&amp;rsquo;s about 25-30% of the reason I watch at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;people-to-gun-for&#34;&gt;People to gun for&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, you&amp;rsquo;re new and that&amp;rsquo;s okay. Here&amp;rsquo;s a cheatsheet on some people I like off the top of my head and why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;ladies&#34;&gt;Ladies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cammy Balanche:&lt;/strong&gt; She all of a sudden got really good a couple of years ago and is now always near the top. If I could go for a beer with any of the ladies, it would be her.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rachel Atherton:&lt;/strong&gt; Fresh off the birth of her first child last year, she&amp;rsquo;s been on top of the game for ages and it will be interesting to see if she can maintain it. I say yes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Myriam Nicole:&lt;/strong&gt; She&amp;rsquo;s french so there&amp;rsquo;s like 50% chance of her winning any given race.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;gentlemen&#34;&gt;Gentlemen&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greg Minaar:&lt;/strong&gt; He&amp;rsquo;s like as old as me and still near the top of his game. Ladies think he&amp;rsquo;s handsome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Troy Brosnan:&lt;/strong&gt; He reminds me a lot of the New Zealand kid Duncan from Bob&amp;rsquo;s Burgers for some reason. But he&amp;rsquo;s Mr. Consistent in that he places like second or third or 50th in every race and I really want to see him win more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finn Iles:&lt;/strong&gt; Him and Mark Wallace are Canada&amp;rsquo;s top dudes and so that&amp;rsquo;s always fun to watch. He&amp;rsquo;s young so he used to crash a lot so hopefully this year he&amp;rsquo;ll be the perfect mix of zesty and italian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reece Wilson:&lt;/strong&gt; He&amp;rsquo;s this young gun who came out of nowhere and is super good. Last year he probably had the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kh15vDDwRGE&#34;&gt;funnest/craziest crash of the whole season&lt;/a&gt; and walked away from it. He also does some announcing and has a fun Scottish accent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gee Atherton:&lt;/strong&gt; In reality, Gee doesn&amp;rsquo;t have much of a chance of winning. The big brother of Rachel (see above), he&amp;rsquo;s had his fair share of the spotlight over the years. If you want to watch a really scary crash video, he went over the bars on a very exposed ridge called the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_hRrA3_MvQ8&#34;&gt;Knife Edge&lt;/a&gt; and ended up spending some time in the hospital and a lot of time doing physical therapy. I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure he&amp;rsquo;s back racing this year, just to be back out there would be a huge accomplishment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of others I could thrown in but they&amp;rsquo;re all just &amp;ldquo;they seem like a good dude/dudette and it would be nice if they won.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;yessss&#34;&gt;Yessss&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should now have a good starting point for getting into watching professional downhill mountain bike racing. I&amp;rsquo;m also excited because we&amp;rsquo;re planning on going to the race at Mont Ste Anne in Québec this year, so if you have any interest in going, starting to watch now is a good starting point to full enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>