<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coding on sad spiders</title>
    <link>https://sadspiders.ca/blog/coding/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coding on sad spiders</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-CA</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2022-2025, the spiders.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 08:40:07 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sadspiders.ca/blog/coding/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Lesson: make other people&#39;s lives easier</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/lesson-make-other-peoples-lives-easier/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 08:40:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/lesson-make-other-peoples-lives-easier/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;dont-make-me-do-extra-work&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t make me do extra work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a lot of years in school. Of those years, four were spent as an undergraduate student. Another ~four were spent as a graduate student. As stupid as those terms are, they let me see life from two different perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, undergrads are stupid idiots who exist to annoy professors and graduate students with their stupidness. Graduate students exist to do the grunt work for professors and annoy postdocs with their stupidness. Part of that grunt work is to mark undergrad papers and assignments so that the professors don&amp;rsquo;t have to. This is what I&amp;rsquo;ll be focusing on today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While an undergraduate, we would chat with the graduate students who would babysit us while doing lab sessions. They hated marking because it&amp;rsquo;s boring and undergrads are stupid. And I realized that since they are human, making their lives easier would like correspond to a better grade. And I think this worked. My work was always well-researched and I put a lot of effort into it. But I would also keep things short and to the point and not wax philosophic about unrelated bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dont-make-me-do-extra-work-1&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t make &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; do extra work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being the type who sometimes makes poor life choices, I eventually became a grad student myself. Indeed, marking papers blows. How did you get to third year and still do &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;, and/or &lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt; so wrong? And I could always tell the people who knew their shit because it was succinct, it was to the point, and it was &lt;em&gt;clear&lt;/em&gt;. If people write an extra 1200 words trying to eke out an extra point or two, you&amp;rsquo;re making me do extra work and now I&amp;rsquo;m grumpy and sinceI am human, will probably give you a slightly lower grade because I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;transferrable-skill&#34;&gt;Transferrable skill&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward a few years to today. I&amp;rsquo;ve got a job as a web developer! I am super smart and can write &lt;em&gt;declarative&lt;/em&gt; code! My code does what it is supposed to! I am really good at this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*submits PR for review *&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;senior dev (to self):&lt;/strong&gt; this is a fucking nightmare&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;senior dev:&lt;/strong&gt; this is a fucking nightmare&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait, what? I am so smrt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;giguh-pr.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;stupid spongebob meme - text says enjoy my giga-pr&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fell prey to one of the classic blunders. I tried to make them do extra work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t make other people do extra work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;keep-it-simple-stupid&#34;&gt;Keep it simple, stupid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back through my &lt;code&gt;diff&lt;/code&gt;, there were a ton of things in there that didn&amp;rsquo;t need to be there. I didn&amp;rsquo;t do as little as possible, and nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you&amp;rsquo;re a junior dev, or looking to get into the field, go through your diff, you can see everything in the &lt;code&gt;changed files&lt;/code&gt; section of your PR on github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look for stuff like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-diff&#34; data-lang=&#34;diff&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#fb4934&#34;&gt;- 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#fb4934&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+ console.log(&amp;#34;test&amp;#34;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+ unusedValue = &amp;#34;works?&amp;#34;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Spend the time to get rid of your goofy shit that doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. We all do it, but the trick is to pretend you don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or stuff like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-diff&#34; data-lang=&#34;diff&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#fb4934&#34;&gt;- id
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#fb4934&#34;&gt;- address {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#fb4934&#34;&gt;-    id
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#fb4934&#34;&gt;-    name    
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#fb4934&#34;&gt;-}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#fb4934&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+ cats
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+ id
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+ dogs
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+ address {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+    id
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+    name
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll need to structure your data like that for clarity or readability and that&amp;rsquo;s totally fine. But you could probably go back and shuffle things around so that the diff just ends up like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-diff&#34; data-lang=&#34;diff&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;id
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+ cats
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;+ dogs
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#282828;background-color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;address {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    ...
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This seems a lot easier to read for the person who will be reviewing your code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While perusing your diff, it&amp;rsquo;s also a good time to assess your functions and variable names and make sure that you&amp;rsquo;re happy with your code and that you won&amp;rsquo;t come back in a month and ask yourself &amp;ldquo;what [eff word]ing idiot wrote this?!&amp;rdquo; before finding that the blame points squarely at you. Try to write code you are proud of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if by doing this you also make less work for your coworkers, all the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-think-at-least&#34;&gt;I think, at least&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, I&amp;rsquo;m a few months into a junior dev role. This seems to make sense to me. There&amp;rsquo;s a quote &lt;a href=&#34;https://quoteinvestigator.com/2011/05/13/einstein-simple/&#34;&gt;attributed to Einstein&lt;/a&gt; whic states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything should be made as simple as possible, but not simpler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and I feel like this is a good application of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can any more experienced devs weigh in? Shout me out, I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/lowpivot&#34;&gt;@lowpivot&lt;/a&gt; and I&amp;rsquo;d really appreciate some feedback. I know this is by no means a deep dive, but I feel like this is an important lesson to learn as a junior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anything else that might seems simple and intuitive but often overlooked by the rookie on the team? Let me know! Thanks, hope this helps somebody.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few quick steps on a long jurney</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/a-few-quick-steps-on-a-long-jurney/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 07:49:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/a-few-quick-steps-on-a-long-jurney/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;i-can-code-just-not-well&#34;&gt;I can code, just not well&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, people generally try hard at what they do. There are definitely going to be exceptions to this, but most people will endeavour to show up every day and do something they can feel at least a little bit proud of. Being a people, I find myself in this category. For better or for worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;lets-keep-this-short&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s keep this short&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like thousands of others before me, yesterday was my first performance review as a junior software developer. Despite many, many hours of study and practice and despite over a year of professional experience, I find myself firmly in the (&lt;em&gt;fucking&lt;/em&gt;) Novice category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ugh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fair enough. As a consummate professional, I take constructive feedback in my stride. But this one hurts a bit. At this point I&amp;rsquo;m not entirely sure why, aside from the obvious fact that no one really likes to be told that they&amp;rsquo;re less good than they&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;think they are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;would like to be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;wang-computers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Martin from &amp;ldquo;The Simpsons&amp;rdquo; wearing his Wang Computers shirt&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;next-steps&#34;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I endeavour to become a proficient software developer, to the point where I may even use the word engineer self-referentially without irony. My next performance review is in three months and I really want to have made some vast strides sinces then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ll use this to light a fire under my own ass and to improve. And hey, why not bl0g the journey so others might learn from my successes and failures. So hopefully I actually have a good reason to write and share posts and others can read along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I can&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rsquo;s not SEO garbage!&amp;quot;™&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;let-me-try-something-first&#34;&gt;Let me try something first&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just want to see if I have the capability to add code fences to this blog:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34; data-lang=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;package&lt;/span&gt; main
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; (
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;fmt&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;func&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fabd2f&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;() {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    fmt.&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fabd2f&#34;&gt;Println&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;Sup, nerds!&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;oh yay I can! I thought I could. And I can &lt;code&gt;inline code snippets&lt;/code&gt; too, I think? Oh good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, let&amp;rsquo;s get it on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I got a job writing code!</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/i-got-a-job-writing-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Mar 2023 15:03:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/i-got-a-job-writing-code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, there&amp;rsquo;s a good chance you are learning to code to try to get a job, attract a mate and live happily ever after. Good for you, what a noble pursuit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a bit of a breakdown of how I got from being someone with some basic HTML and CSS knowledge to the hack that I am today, with a superficial knowledge of a hundred other technologies. Strap in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction-the-why-of-it-all&#34;&gt;Introduction: The &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; of it all.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t do things &amp;ldquo;just because&amp;rdquo;. Ha ha yeah I totally do but maybe not this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s jump into the story in about 2016 or thereabouts. I had myself a Raspberry Pi model 3B+ and was teaching myself the basics of Linux. I kept coming across people talking about writing scripts in Python, so I decide to try doing that. I stumbled across the website &lt;a href=&#34;https://automatetheboringstuff.com/&#34;&gt;Automate the Boring Stuff&lt;/a&gt; because I hate boring stuff and spent some time going through that publication from cover to cover. Neat, I can program stuff now! I tried writing a program to automate some of the boring bullshit for my day job and.. ..it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work we run Windows computers without Python installed, so I need to strap an entire Python interpreter into an &lt;em&gt;exe&lt;/em&gt; file and the whole thing just sort of reeks of hackiness. I am not impressed. So I abandon that ship and just keep doing the boring shit the old fashioned way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-webserver&#34;&gt;The Webserver&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first attempt at doing programming stuff has taught me that I need to learn more about how the web works. I start working on a website to crowdsource mountain bike trail conditions using Python and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://flask.palletsprojects.com/en/2.2.x/&#34;&gt;Flask framework&lt;/a&gt; using a great tutorial by &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.miguelgrinberg.com/post/the-flask-mega-tutorial-part-i-hello-world&#34;&gt;Miguel Grinberg&lt;/a&gt;. It went well, and I learned more about relational databases (MySQL in this case) and reverse proxies (nginx) and hosted the whole thing on the Raspberry pi. It&amp;rsquo;s sweet! But no one really uses it and in retrospect it could have been done a lot better but that&amp;rsquo;s also a good thing - I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot since then!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-pandemic&#34;&gt;The Pandemic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My website was sort of crappy and no one used it and I was working full time in an analytical chemistry laboratory and didn&amp;rsquo;t really know where this whole thing was headed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the pandemic hit and the world lost it&amp;rsquo;s collective shit, and fair enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took advantage of this time to create some Python-based scripts to do some web scraping of some work-related websites that never really went anywhere. I was still working in the lab a few days a week because my job was &lt;em&gt;essential&lt;/em&gt; but with my extra time I came across the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fullstackopen.com/en/&#34;&gt;Full Stack Open&lt;/a&gt; course through the University of Helsinki. Was I ready to learn &lt;em&gt;React&lt;/em&gt;? Isn&amp;rsquo;t React for smart people? What the fuck is it, anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent a few week and went through the entire course, diligently completing all of the examples and assignments. Look at me, using javascript like a champ to make a webpage that is &lt;em&gt;reactive&lt;/em&gt;. Being able to launch apps on Netlify was a game-changer for me, I could finally implement a bunch of these websites for my day job to process my instrument data and save myself multiple minutes a day! React rules! Except I don&amp;rsquo;t really like using Redux and there&amp;rsquo;s something about it that rubs me the wrong way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also I learned Git at this point. Fuck yeah!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-svelte&#34;&gt;Enter Svelte&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t rememeber how I stumbed across &lt;a href=&#34;https://svelte.dev/&#34;&gt;Svelte&lt;/a&gt;, but it seemed like a next-gen version of React where all the hacky shit had been replaced with native support. I set up an app using their website builder called Sapper. It seemed okay, but I was still lost with respect to web development. There&amp;rsquo;s literally a trillion technologies out there. What&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://go.dev&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt; like?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-go&#34;&gt;Enter Go&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason I thought that maybe I was a back-end guy. The internet fucking sucks sometimes, you know? I don&amp;rsquo;t want to serve ads or collect user data or any of this shit. Maybe writing backend code will give me some sort of bigger purpose, maybe I can crunch data that climate scientists use to make the world actually better. This is a theme I struggle with constantly. Very existential but ultimately unanswerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read some sort of introductory book on Go from cover to cover and performed and the exercises. Woo, Go! The best part is using the walrus-operator to assign variables:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-go&#34; data-lang=&#34;go&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;number &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#d3869b&#34;&gt;42&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;See? Walrus! I&amp;rsquo;m also fully aware of the difference between a dynamically-typed language and a statically-type language. Neat! I like that while I&amp;rsquo;m writing Go in VSCode that I&amp;rsquo;ve got code autocomplation thanks to the strongly-typed variables, even though there are still a few concepts that elude me (looking at you, &lt;em&gt;interfaces&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, great, now I&amp;rsquo;m a backend guy a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;backend-is-stupid&#34;&gt;Backend is stupid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I quickly have nothing to program on the backend and Go is a bit scary, what with concurrency and pointers and whatnot. Furthermore, &lt;a href=&#34;https://kit.svelte.dev&#34;&gt;Sveltekit&lt;/a&gt; is a thing now! Neat! I program another couple of little projects using Sveltekit. Holy shit, React is so shitty compared to Sveltekit! I make the decision that I would rather compete for the scarce few Sveltekit jobs rather than ever have to touch React again. I am firmly a Sveltekit guy and as much of a Rich Harris fanboy as you can be at middle-age. Sveltekit is also basically it&amp;rsquo;s own server, so we can just do everything in javascript!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;learn-all-of-the-things&#34;&gt;Learn all of the things&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now what? At this point I&amp;rsquo;ve dabbled in literally a fuckton of different languages and frameworks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTML, CSS, SASS, LESS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Node, Express, Svelte, Sveltekit, React, Redux, Flask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bootstrap, Foundation,Tailwind&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript, Python, Go&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apache, nginx&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MySQL, sqlite, MongoDB, Mongoose, Prisma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure there are others that I tried for an hour or two and dismissed, but these are all at least things I have basic proficiency with. My favourite stack has become a sqlite database with sveltekit frontend and prisma acting as the go-between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;interlude-my-day-job-it-department-hates-me-until-they-dont&#34;&gt;Interlude: My Day-job It Department Hates me. Until they don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still working full-time in the lab throughout this whole process, and have offered to moonlight in the IT department and also have learned a ton of SQL in an effort to become the new database administrator to no avail. Boo. Annoyed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, a friend that works in the department vouched for me as a reasonably-competent developer, and I get a one-year contract to develop an in-house e-commerce-type site. Woohoo, coding for a living, suck it everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project ends up being a success, I am able to ship the projects thanks to the batteries-included &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.djangoproject.com/&#34;&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; project. In the end I think the whole thing is a bit hacky, but it has been used in production for nine months at the time I am writing this with no major crap-ups so I&amp;rsquo;m calling that a win! This was a nice little opportunity that I am happy to have on my resume. Networking ftw! Except I still hate LinkedIn and pretty sure I always will. But if you like it and it works for you, power to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;typescript-btw&#34;&gt;Typescript, btw&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;m getting deep into the workings of Sveltekit, I am noticing that for some reason they are all about Typescript. I assume, naturally, that I am too stupid to understand Typescript but decide to have a go at it. I dabbled a bit during the Full Stack Open course and was definitely less-than-impressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I read the entire &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/programming-typescript/9781492037644/&#34;&gt;Programming Tpyescript&lt;/a&gt; book and skimmed the parts that were over my head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spun up a new Sveltekit project to much around with. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a learning curve for sure and I spend a fair amount of time going through the Sveltekit docs to figure out what sort of types need to be assigned to some default variables, but nothing too crazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it turns out, Typescript is fucking awesome. I had heard that it was too much overhead for small projects, but the amount of time I was saving thanks to my IDE&amp;rsquo;s autocompletion is super-great. Getting screwed by inappropriate return types in my functions screwed me a couple of times during my Django project, so I appreciate knowing exactly what each variable looks like and what sort of parameters it might have available instead of &lt;code&gt;console.log&lt;/code&gt;ging things until they work. I still do that, but just less now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;going-for-the-win&#34;&gt;Going for the win&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point I am back in the lab and want to find a full-time remote gig. I&amp;rsquo;ve got my stack of choice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sveltekit + Typescript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PostgreSQL database&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://prisma.io&#34;&gt;Prisma&lt;/a&gt; ORM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe some Go because I still like Go even though it&amp;rsquo;s not Rust btw&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to be able to tell prospective employers that I&amp;rsquo;ve got collaborative experience using Git, I create the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jeffreycharters/station&#34;&gt;STaTioN&lt;/a&gt; repository. It consists of the very basic building blocks of a modern website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;script.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initiate those files with a very basic amount of data and ask some of my Twitter friends to get involved if they so choose. They do! It&amp;rsquo;s kind of awesome learning how to deal with Pull Requests and issues and all that type of stuff with no real &amp;ldquo;Prod&amp;rdquo; to break, and if you do no one really cares because it&amp;rsquo;s all just there to break anyway. Thanks for getting involved, everyone! I&amp;rsquo;ve let the site stagnate, I sometimes think about torching it all back down to the very basics and starting over. We&amp;rsquo;ll see, maybe?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;finally-a-job&#34;&gt;Finally a job&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I applied to many, many places. However, I was also deliberate with my applications. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe in the &amp;ldquo;spray &amp;rsquo;n&amp;rsquo; pray&amp;rdquo; school of thought. My cover letters were all tailored to the individual position. I got a couple of interviews, which was promising, and also a lot of radio-silence, which was not. So I just kept applying. I found jobs via the usual job sites, I looked for local developers and contacted them directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My break into the field came from a job ad on the Svelte Discord server&amp;rsquo;s job section. Sveltekit had reached the &lt;strong&gt;Verion 1.0&lt;/strong&gt; milestone which means &amp;ldquo;yeah use this in production now, I don&amp;rsquo;t give a shit&amp;rdquo; which I think gave more employers the confidence to deploy their Sveltekit projects. The company promised resume-free hiring, which is super awesome because resumes are stupid and no one really knows if they&amp;rsquo;re doing them right and the whole thing can just use an overhaul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I went through their process, did an online interview, and they got in touch a week or so later with a job offer! Woooo work-from-home FTW!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ᄽ(ノ◕⌢◕)ᄽノ ︵ ┻━┻&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; The new employer&amp;rsquo;s backend is written in Go and is actually a GraphQL server. So I actually get to write Go professionally! Nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;postamble&#34;&gt;Postamble&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;computer-guy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The fat nerdy computer guy from South Park and he&amp;rsquo;s got some mountain dew&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s it. I spent a number of years during my evenings and weekends teaching myself to write code and now I have a job where I sit at home all day and write code. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to get fat though since I enjoy endurance cycling and regular mountain biking and rock climbing and all sort of other shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-advice&#34;&gt;My Advice&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you read this fucking thing? You don&amp;rsquo;t want my advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you insist, pick some shit you like and start writing code. Keep up to date with things, the field changes every 3 or 4 days and you need to learn a new language or framework or some other shit. Give up and become an electrician or plumber or something. But I guess in the end I&amp;rsquo;m proof that you can get started on a career as a programmer for basically no monies as long as you have unlimited time to spend learning all this shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do like it though, really.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Al Gore-isms</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/al-gore-isms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Nov 2022 17:46:20 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/al-gore-isms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;its-a-book-stupid&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a book, stupid.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw on &lt;em&gt;Twitter&lt;/em&gt; that someone was reading the book &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Algorithms&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; by Panos Louridas and someone else commented that it was a good read. So, being the good nerd that I am, I raced out and got myself a copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t read too much yet, maybe two or three chapters. Enough to cover the majority of Dijkstra&amp;rsquo;s Algorithm. And it made me realize something:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just effing &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt; living in the &amp;ldquo;valley of despair&amp;rdquo; in a Dunning-Kruger knowledge/perceived-knowledge figure. For some reason I am fascinated by how much smarter other people are than myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1337c0d3-v-me&#34;&gt;1337c0d3 v. me&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know where my future career is going to go. I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning a ton in order to do web development effectively. Here&amp;rsquo;s a few of the things I&amp;rsquo;ve needed to learn to get here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;python and then Flask and Django, the web frameworks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;javascript, and then React and Sveltekit, the web frameworks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTML and CSS so I can make websites that don&amp;rsquo;t look like a dog&amp;rsquo;s breakfast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SQL and relational databases, so I can store data effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nodejs and Express to be able to program a webserver.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to use version control software and collaborate with others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to set up an nginx reverse proxy and load balancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I still have that sinking feeling of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;wtf am I doing here? I like the internet, but 99.8% of it is porno or advertising or marketing or social mediae and I don&amp;rsquo;t want any part of those things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-algorithms&#34;&gt;Enter algorithms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things are generally pretty good. I spent a year doing web dev work for my current employer. My &lt;a href=&#34;https://station-team.netlify.app&#34;&gt;little open-source project&lt;/a&gt; had some traction and was good to introduce people to making Github pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I feel like I want to get deeper. To go behing the scenes. I don&amp;rsquo;t even know doing what. To crunch data, to make things run more efficiently. And algorithms seem to be a crucial step in that process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we&amp;rsquo;ll see where this goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as mentioned earlier, it seems like I&amp;rsquo;m standing at the bottom of a huge mountain, looking up and being baffled that I might even take a few footsteps up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But moving forward is what we must do. Otherwise I get bored and overwhelmed by the shitty state of society/planet, so a distraction is a requirement. Right now, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a small amount of graph theory and how to find the shortest path between two points using a non-greedy algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned. Hopefully things get nerdy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gravel season returns, set your goals</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/gravel-season-returns-set-your-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 08:35:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/gravel-season-returns-set-your-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summers-almost-over&#34;&gt;SUMMER&amp;rsquo;S ALMOST OVER!!!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As August draws to a close, let&amp;rsquo;s all take a moment to remind it that we all hate it and it&amp;rsquo;s a shitty month and it can fuck off. And take February with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;set-your-goals&#34;&gt;Set Your Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, August is almost over and I haven&amp;rsquo;t got out mountain biking nearly as much as I would have liked, but that&amp;rsquo;s okay. A lot of life has been happening, and we deal with it a day at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spring, you will recall that I finally accomplished my goal of &lt;a href=&#34;../the-windiest-135km-bike-ride/&#34;&gt;doing the 100km+ ride&lt;/a&gt; from our home to my gfs family&amp;rsquo;s farm for Easter. This was my first ride to cross the 100km mark and the conditions were sub-optimal. The windiest day of the year so far as a crosswind definitely didn&amp;rsquo;t make that ride any easier and I was not in the greatest spirits as we crossed the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the obvious thing to do is to create a new, more ambitious goal. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myself and my bicycle, Grimey, will hereby attempt to complete an &amp;ldquo;imperial century&amp;rdquo; ride of 100 miles or more by the end of October of this year. We begin at Buckingham Palace and the Queen herself will drop the green flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I will be renaming our house Buckingham Palace for the occasion and Ashley will be happy to accept the Queen monicker until the mutinies start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;that-sounds-awful&#34;&gt;That sounds awful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s funny because we all keep up with our own version of the Joneses. My youtube feed is full of 150 or more mile ultra-endurance races, so doing a ride like this seems quite tame in comparison. But I mention it to normies (aka friends and family) and they are quick to point out that how do you do that it&amp;rsquo;s so far? Same way as you eat an elephant I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;making-a-plan&#34;&gt;Making a plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this ride will be in less than two months, and possibly within a month or so. Which does not leave a heap of time for training and conditioning. Shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll create a more formal plan for myself, but in the meantime, how to prepare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend more time on the bike. Just in general. Get the body used to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hill training. Head out for less than an hour and repeatedly ride up the biggest hills in the area at full gas, recover on the way back down. It&amp;rsquo;s high-intensity intervals and it sucks but it will build some strength and should hopefully provide quick/substantial cardiovascular gains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longer, mellow rides. Head out to the rail trails and just cruise for two hours or more. Sometimes go for a second ride that day, make sure the body is okay with having to go when it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really want to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eat and ride. When you&amp;rsquo;re out for extended rides and want to make good time, you need to train your body to expend energy and digest at the same time. So bring a substantial snack to eat at the start of the ride, or even at the halfway point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the last ride, my guts felt gross in the second half from eating the [high-calories == crap] food, so I might need to experiment with this a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stay-tuned&#34;&gt;Stay tuned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last ride clocked in around 135km and lasted about seven hours, I think? So planning to tack on another hour, which hopefully won&amp;rsquo;t destroy me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone want to loan me a drone and wants to come out for a small section to get some aerial shots, that&amp;rsquo;d be awesome. No pay!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll keep you posted as we move towards R-day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Project: DH Bike Plates</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 08:30:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction---problem-description&#34;&gt;Introduction - Problem Description&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As everyone who knows me knows, it is not often that you can get through a conversation with me without having bikes come up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since I am a lot lazier than people like to think, I would rather watch biking than participate. So every year I make sure to follow the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uci.org/calendar/mtb/1voMyukVGR4iZMhMlDfRv0?discipline=MTB&#34;&gt;UCI Downhill Mountain Bike World Cup&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Union Cycliste Internationale&lt;/em&gt;) and watch all of the races lives where possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the run-up to each event, a number of media outlets provide video of practice runs to get an idea of what the track is looking like and how various riders are tackling the difficult sections of track. Althought I very much appreciate what they do, it irks me a bit that they don&amp;rsquo;t include each rider&amp;rsquo;s name on screen to know whom&amp;rsquo;s who. Further complicating things, the plate number for each rider changes &lt;em&gt;every single stupid race&lt;/em&gt;, which means you can&amp;rsquo;t even just memorize plate  numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-solution&#34;&gt;My solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the plate number is based on the riders&amp;rsquo; current UCI ranking, I&amp;rsquo;m going to take the information from UCI&amp;rsquo;s website and add it to a database using &lt;a href=&#34;https://planetscale.com&#34;&gt;Planetscale&lt;/a&gt; and their generous free tier to see hwow things go. I want to add Prisma as on ORM because I like using Prisma as an ORM. I&amp;rsquo;ll start out by simply creating a backend API using TypeScript and &lt;a href=&#34;http://expressjs.com&#34;&gt;Express&lt;/a&gt;. It will start out being &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; bare-bones, since I want this up and running by mid-week in it&amp;rsquo;s most basic form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I have the backend up, I will write a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; simple front-end, probably using Svelte (and Tailwind for prettification) to consume the API. Since this is going to be primarily a mobile app so I can use it while plopped in front of the TV, I have grand plans of using a touch-based quick-scroll mechanism, I&amp;rsquo;ll see how easy that will be to implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short term, I may just have to print the information on-screen and have a font-size adjuster so we can get the information as quickly available as possible. This is required because there is no real pattern in the footage being shown in these videos &amp;ndash; you may need to jump from plate 35 of the Elite Women to plate 87 for Elite Men to plate 1 of the Junior Men, so an intuitive interface will be required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;downsides&#34;&gt;Downsides&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really want to write a project using Test-Driven Development (TDD). Unfortunately, I want this done &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt; so it won&amp;rsquo;t happen right yet. However, I may continue this project into the winter which could allow for TDD of future functionality. My time limit and &amp;ldquo;would rather have it work than work well&amp;rdquo; attitude wil preclude &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; unit testing during the initial roll-out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; set up dummy data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; set up basic API with Express&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; set up Planetscale DB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; write Prisma schema and sync with DB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; verify API works as expected&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; make entire front-end first?!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;deadline&#34;&gt;Deadline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a race this week, meaning footage should start rolling out in about two or three days. I want to have &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; in place and working by then. Even if it&amp;rsquo;s just a big list of all the riders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Best case:&lt;/strong&gt;



























&lt;img 
  sizes=&#34;(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw&#34;
  srcset=&#39;https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/best-case_hu4972109061168556998.jpg 500w, https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/best-case_hu4011339289667783077.jpg 800w, https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/best-case_hu6747575091073472814.jpg 1200w&#39;
  
    src=&#34;https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/best-case.jpg&#34; 
  
  alt=&#34;Stylish rider jumping between two trees&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worst case:&lt;/strong&gt;



























&lt;img 
  sizes=&#34;(min-width: 35em) 1200px, 100vw&#34;
  srcset=&#39;https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/worst-case_hu5510906766473660246.jpg 500w, https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/worst-case_hu8367088164697626681.jpg 800w, https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/worst-case_hu765702448599650213.jpg 1200w&#39;
  
    src=&#34;https://sadspiders.ca/new-project-dh-bike-plates/worst-case.jpg&#34; 
  
  alt=&#34;Rider on their back after a crash with their bike airborne beside them&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the flipside, there&amp;rsquo;s a race next weekend! I encourage everyone to get on board, it&amp;rsquo;s exciting to watch!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Javascript: A Use for Classes!</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/javascript-a-use-for-classes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 08:30:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/javascript-a-use-for-classes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-awww-shoot&#34;&gt;Update! Awww shoot.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really excited to give these classes a whirl when reality came crashing down on me, so I thought I would share what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In certain scenarios, like writing backend code, this would have been a great use of classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, turns out that using this in a reactive frontend framework (SvelteKit) is a recipe for heartbreak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I manually added a user to my monthly bills, and then tried using the UI to remove them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They were removed from the object!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, this was not reflected on the screen, where nothing happened.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in order to make my object reactive, I would have to do something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;bills.removePerson(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;jeffrey&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;)
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;bills &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; bills
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a perfect cromulent way of doing it, but it feels.. ..hacky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To remedy the situation, I will be creating a &lt;a href=&#34;https://svelte.dev/tutorial/writable-stores&#34;&gt;store&lt;/a&gt; that will keep track of my application state, which will be using the framework as intended instead of forcing my will upon it. I&amp;rsquo;m going to dwell on the best way to make things happen, I will write a post in the future once I have figured out the optimal way to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initial post below the break for posterity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;build-in-public&#34;&gt;Build in Public&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently mentioned on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.com/channels/932253730605252609&#34;&gt;Self-taught Tech Network&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Discord server that I was confused on when to use classes when programming. The server&amp;rsquo;s administrator and probably-not-a-psychpath (Joel)[https://twitter.com/TechPickleJoel] chimed in the remind me with the principle I needed to be reminded of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s know [sic] as separation of concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Editor&amp;rsquo;s note:&lt;/strong&gt; Please don&amp;rsquo;t judge him by his typo, he had no idea it would be published for millions to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, the pins started falling into place in my understand of when to use classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-domesticity&#34;&gt;Enter domesticity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every month or so, my sig oth and I make a pile of receipts and figure out whom owes who how much money over the course of the month. So I dutifully open google sheets and enter some values into some columns and life moves another step forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you may be aware, I am trying to forcefully shove my career direction into the web development direction. And since it&amp;rsquo;s fun to spend several weekends and evenings to make a web app to save myself five minutes worth of work a month, I&amp;rsquo;m going to develop an app!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./glootie.png&#34; alt=&#34;A screen grab from Rick and Morty. The character named Glootie has a tattoo on his forehead which reads &amp;ldquo;Do not develop my app&amp;rdquo;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;class-is-in-session-&#34;&gt;Class is in session 😎&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While trying to determine the bits and bobs that would be required for this app I realized something: a month can be a class!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be a number of components to a month, and I think everything would be easier if I abstracted a lot of logic into its own file. Some examples should help here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-original-idea&#34;&gt;The original idea&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, I had considered making the month as a dictionary, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; bills &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  month&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;June&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  people&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; [&lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;j&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;o&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;],
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  recurring&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; [
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      name&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;electric&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      amount: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fabd2f&#34;&gt;25.34&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      }
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  ],
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  receipts&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; [
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      location&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;GroceryCo&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      date: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fabd2f&#34;&gt;1657457787&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      amount: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fabd2f&#34;&gt;123.45&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;      comment&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;ignore bike parts for me&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    }
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  ]
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nothing too complicated here. It&amp;rsquo;s got the month, the people involed, and lists of monthly bills and the receipts we have lying around. But if I were to put my logic in with the rest of my code, this could get ugly in a hurry. For instance, if I decide I want to see the receipts in chronological order, I need to create a new function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;// this could be made a one-liner, but for clarity...
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; receiptsChrono &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; (receipts) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  list.sort((a, b) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; (a.date &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; b.date) &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;?&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#d3869b&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#d3869b&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;);
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is fine, but to use it in multiple places I will need to place it into it&amp;rsquo;s own file and import it wherever it is needed. So if I create a file which exports this function, it will need to be imported as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; { receiptsChrono } &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;./some/dir/receiptUtils.ts&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I add more functions, I could export them all from the &lt;code&gt;receiptUtils.ts&lt;/code&gt; file at the same time, which would make life easier, but this is still not ideal because I will have a dictionary of the months, but all of the functions to manipulate them will be in a different file. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; receiptUtils &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;./some/dir/receiptUtils.ts&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;bills &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;// ..see bills dictionary in above example
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;}
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;sortedBills &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; receiptUtils.receiptsChorono(bills.receipts);
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;console.log(sortedBills);
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;// output: list of bills sorted chronologically
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h4 id=&#34;now-lets-do-it-with-classes&#34;&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s do it with classes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s make life easier on me, since that&amp;rsquo;s the whole point of computers until they rise up and either kill us all or get solar-flared into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of a dictionary, my month of bills is going to be a class I will call Month, since it is a month of bills. I am doing this in typescript, so if something looks weird to you you can probably safely ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;// month.ts
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; Month {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  month: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fabd2f&#34;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;constructor&lt;/span&gt;(month: &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fabd2f&#34;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt;) {
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;.month &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; month
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;  }
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;} 
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the very start of my class, since it is still a work in progress. Hopefully I write more once the project is further along, so stay tuned or sign up to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sadspiders.ca/index.xml&#34;&gt;RSS Feed&lt;/a&gt; to get it delivered to your feed-reader like a good nerd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BUT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how this is going to work. First, I will import and create an instance of this class:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; month &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; Month(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;june&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;);
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;console.log(month.month);
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;// output: &amp;#34;june&amp;#34;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s great. I&amp;rsquo;m planning to write some setters, setters and methods in order to manipulate the object that has been made using this class. This will help to &lt;em&gt;encapsulate&lt;/em&gt; the logic, rather than have it spread out all over the place. The example above was used to create a variable that stored the chronologically-sorted receipts which would then be logged. But using a class, this logic can easily be accessed with less verbosity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; { Month } &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;./some/dir/month.ts&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; month &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; Month(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;June&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;);
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;// we need to imagine we have added some receipts to &amp;#39;month&amp;#39;.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;console.log(month.receiptsChrono())
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;// output: list of bills sorted chronologically
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;As you can see, this code is probably more readable than using a dictionary and functions. You can still figure out what is going on, but we have been able to remove a few boilerplatey lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;onwards&#34;&gt;Onwards!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been pretty off-the-cuff writing since I am excited to have found a use for classes in a project I am working on. I am looking forward to determining which methods will be useful for this class and am interested to see how the development of this app goes with a new tool to play with. Even as far as the output of this application goes, I am hoping to simply have a method that can be called as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#ebdbb2;background-color:#282828;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-typescript&#34; data-lang=&#34;typescript&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;console.log(month.output(format&lt;span style=&#34;color:#fe8019&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#b8bb26&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;csv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;));
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#928374;font-style:italic&#34;&gt;// output: a csv file of my data!
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post is proof that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://discord.com/channels/932253730605252609&#34;&gt;Self-taught Tech Network&lt;/a&gt; can help to up your coding game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time, keep fit and have fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./bodybreak.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Hal Johnson and Joanne McCleoud in front of the Body Break logo&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing your first Sveltekit app</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/writing-your-first-sveltekit-app/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 16:42:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/writing-your-first-sveltekit-app/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;preamble-aka-tldr-1-of-2&#34;&gt;Preamble (aka tl;dr 1 of 2)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal of the moment is to get some sort of gig as a web developer so I can work remotely and get more and more into libertarianism until nobody wants to hang out with me anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the requirements, according to the internet, is to create a lot of bullshit, copy-paste style content that thousands of other people have written but better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;get-a-modem-and-a-geocities-account&#34;&gt;Get a modem and a Geocities account&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My adventure begins somewhere around 1995, when the internet sort of sucked and no one really knew what it&amp;rsquo;s deal was. We got a computer that had an icon that said &amp;ldquo;Internet&amp;rdquo; and that was great. I was able to use my couple-of-dozen kilobauds per second of transfer speed to get myself a Geocities account. &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20010512060621/http://www.geocities.com/SunsetStrip/Towers/2226/&#34;&gt;Archive link&lt;/a&gt;. It sucks multiple types of shit and tries to download a Blink 182 MIDI file when you view it. It had a guestbook. A sad, sad guestbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was interested in creating website stuff, but had no gdf clue how. So I applied to the &amp;ldquo;New Media&amp;rdquo; program at a semi-local university and failed to gain acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;say-fuck-it&#34;&gt;Say &amp;ldquo;fuck it&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When life hands you lemons, do something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash;Glarg Barbidov&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, become a bike messenger in a major metropolitan area for a while. It might be the best job you ever have. Working outside, not paying taxes on your income, life is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;see-the-world&#34;&gt;See the world&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Head to Austrlia for a year. Pick mangoes. Surf. Buy a camper van whoms engine seizes the next day leaving you out $1500 that you really can&amp;rsquo;t afford. Bartend in a ghost town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;create-content&#34;&gt;Create content&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a while there were the blogs called &amp;ldquo;E/N&amp;rdquo; blogs, or everything/nothing. You know, like this one. No clear objective, just some idiot pouring their brain into a keyboard for kicks and for a few laughs with their friends. We didn&amp;rsquo;t lol in those days. I still don&amp;rsquo;t. I made one where I created each blog post in it&amp;rsquo;s own HTML file, dilligently copying and pasting from the previous HTML file, and then adding the new blog to my list of blogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect it makes me so angry that I did things this way. There had to have been some sort of easier way, even at this point, no? Even if I had a &lt;code&gt;/cgi-bin/&lt;/code&gt; directory? Remember those? When computer graphics started appearing in movies and people said the &lt;code&gt;cgi&lt;/code&gt; of a movie was good/bad I just thought &amp;ldquo;common gateway interface.&amp;rdquo; I do a lot of things weird, I think. I feel like this is almost as bad as &amp;ldquo;hold me closer, Tony Danza.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh hey, almost forgot, there&amp;rsquo;s an archived version &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.archive.org/web/20040130215445/http://unfun.robotskull.com/&#34;&gt;Unfun&lt;/a&gt; as well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember when your website had a button?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was mine &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; &lt;img src=&#34;./bouton.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Button to visit Unfun, my old website. The text reads  &amp;ldquo;more meow, more wang, more blog, more wacky stunts. Unfun - ultra-sexy&#34;&gt; Yes, there&amp;rsquo;s a hand-drawn weiner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;get-educated&#34;&gt;Get educated&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A four-year degree in Environmental Chemistry with pretty much nothing to do with webdev is what you think will be a good use of your time. Oh hey but on the plus side I was elected Editor-in-Chief of a campus publication and got to lead people and design a product, along with promotional pins! Everyone loves pins! Well, they did in 2007 and they still should. &amp;lt;/ oldManMode &amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel inspired that you are actually good at something. Good at &lt;em&gt;science&lt;/em&gt;. You will change the world someday!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;get-more-educated&#34;&gt;Get more educated&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And make sure you go to the opposite side of the country to do so. Can&amp;rsquo;t really complain too hard about this one, got to sail on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://archives.whoi.edu/beaufortgyre/www.whoi.edu/page.do@pid=66558.html&#34;&gt;Coast Guard icebreaker&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://archives.whoi.edu/beaufortgyre/www.whoi.edu/page.do@pid=66518.html&#34;&gt;twice!&lt;/a&gt;), snowboard lots, caught crabs (on a beach, not the yuck kind) (no judgment) and did a decent amount of snowboarding and downhill mountain biking. Create a pretty crummy website for your research group that never really gets used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way you can learn a bit of javascript but not so much to be really useful with anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel a bit crushed that your love of science actually doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean jack shit because there are 350 million other people intent on changing the world and you&amp;rsquo;re just kinda.. ..in there somewhere, not really excelling at anything. The path of least resistance has become a forest of lots of resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;find-a-job-doing-something-meh&#34;&gt;Find a job doing something meh&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work in a lab! Be part of a union! This isn&amp;rsquo;t so much changing the world as.. ..being a part of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read all the news you want, and get angry about it! But all you really do is vote every 2 years or so (provincial and federali elections) and that&amp;rsquo;s about it, bub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also what the shit, how have twenty years passed since that Geocities nonsense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what, screw it. The world effing sucks (in some ways) and it&amp;rsquo;s not my problem anymore. I&amp;rsquo;ve been riding to school/work for most of my life, I hang-dry my clothes, I use Amazon infrequently. I just want to get a job doing something I don&amp;rsquo;t hate and spend the rest of my time biking and laying on the floor with dogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*googles how to do code writing*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*reads &lt;a href=&#34;https://automatetheboringstuff.com&#34;&gt;automate the boring stuff&lt;/a&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Used &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.miguelgrinberg.com/post/the-flask-mega-tutorial-part-i-hello-world&#34;&gt;Miguel Grinberg&amp;rsquo;s Flask Megatutorial&lt;/a&gt; to learn enough Python/Flask create a mountain bike trail status crowdsourcing website called Radriders. It never gains any traction. Boo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;interlude&#34;&gt;Interlude&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, then this whole global pandemic thing happened. WORK FROM HOME?! I work in a lab and didn&amp;rsquo;t really get much of a break during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, my experience was much, much worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had some sort of mental breakdown/burnout and I was honestly worried that I had broken my brain and I would never be able to absorb as much complexity as an episode of Friends has to offer. It was bad. Thank the good lord for youtube videos of train rides in the rain. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bQd9aHWXF6U&#34;&gt;Seriously&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve watched that train video like 30 times. That&amp;rsquo;s exactly the level of complexity my brain was capable of handling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my recent claims to the contrary, we got a few sparse days of working from home. I had learned a bit of javascript along the way, so I decided to tackle the course from the University of Helsinki entitled &lt;a href=&#34;https://fullstackopen.com/en/&#34;&gt;Deep Dive Into Modern Web Development&lt;/a&gt;. It taught me React+Redux, Express, MongoDB and a bit of Typescript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;opportunity&#34;&gt;Opportunity!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My work hired some other person to create a website that has apparently been in the works for eons. Well, maybe only one eon, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be dramatic. He quit because some bank was going to pay him mad skrilla to do something for them. I feel sorry for the bank because I get hired on for the role and his code is.. ..uh.. ..fine. The directive from the powers-that-be is that this project needs to be done &amp;ldquo;like yesterday.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I convince my boss that we&amp;rsquo;re better off scrapping his codebase using Django Rest Framework and React and just going with straight-up Django. I figure this will eliminate any of the complexity involved with passing info between two different frameworks and I am super-right. The site launches months later and is so-far well-received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this time also developed another app using Django to allow another group of clients to display &lt;a href=&#34;https://iapd.lsd.uoguelph.ca&#34;&gt;Animal Disease Dashboards&lt;/a&gt; for veterinarians and researches in the area. Simple but effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;python-sucks&#34;&gt;Python sucks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rescind that third-level header, python doesn&amp;rsquo;t sucks. Python&amp;rsquo;s really great for somethings, but I&amp;rsquo;ve already been effed in the ay by expecting an integer and being given a string, and when comparing 40 and &amp;ldquo;40&amp;rdquo; having the application say &amp;ldquo;no these are obviously not the same *flips over and dies*&amp;rdquo; and it&amp;rsquo;s not ideal. I decide I want type-safety. Also everyone on the internet talks trash about React and I&amp;rsquo;ve heard good things about &lt;a href=&#34;https://svelte.dev&#34;&gt;Svelte&lt;/a&gt; and the internet seems to be mildly infatuated with it so let&amp;rsquo;s have a look! Hey, I like it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They have this other weird thing called &amp;ldquo;Sapper&amp;rdquo; and I don&amp;rsquo;t really know what it is so I just monkey around with Svelte a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-sveltekit&#34;&gt;Enter Sveltekit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sapper grew up and became &lt;a href=&#34;https://kit.svelte.dev&#34;&gt;SvelteKit&lt;/a&gt; and all of a sudden this framework is the real deal. It&amp;rsquo;s like if React got ran over with a Roomba and now everything is just easier and nicer and better and it takes a lot less time to do what I want. I&amp;rsquo;m a pretty hardened nerd by this point, so I do my best to learn from the official documentation and then quickly consult youtube (hey, twice in one post!) for some tutorials because I get lost quickly. And whoa, it&amp;rsquo;s really great. And easy. ish. Nothing easy is worth doing. *resists tempation to make crass joke, but still needs you to know he knows it&amp;rsquo;s there*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;creating-the-website&#34;&gt;Creating the website&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My idea was to create a microtweeting website, which I have &lt;a href=&#34;../blurt-have-i-become&#34;&gt;mentioned before&lt;/a&gt;. So then once you have installed Sveltekit and learned how to use it, just program the functionality you need. Easy! Also if you want it to be type-safe, write it in Typescript! If you get stuck there are literally a billion tutorials out there, probably actually an underestimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://prisma.io&#34;&gt;Prisma&lt;/a&gt; for an object-relational model (ORM) and it was awesome, use Prisma! (yo Prisma, send me some stickers or something!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hire-me&#34;&gt;Hire Me!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone wants to offer me any sort of remote job using Sveltekit and pay me a decent salary I will jump on it. I am great to work with, learn quick and good, also good at &lt;a href=&#34;../the-windiest-135km-bike-ride/&#34;&gt;riding bikes&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s some shit I can computer do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTML&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSS (incl. SASS, tailwind)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Javascript (but not Java)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;React, Redux, Sveltekit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python/Django/Flask&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Video Editing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up an nginx server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Svelte and Sveltekit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Typescript&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a mean SQL query&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design/normalize relational databases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Markdown!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unit tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;postamble-aka-tldr-2-of-2&#34;&gt;Postamble (aka tl;dr 2 of 2)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t normally include a postamble but here we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the trick is to work on various things that aren&amp;rsquo;t web development, then spend a few years learning javascript and python and eventually Typescript. Once you learn React you will be excited to learn any other web development framework that isn&amp;rsquo;t React. At this point, learn Sveltekit and create your application!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure to host it on the Raspberry Pi in your basement or the hardcore nerds won&amp;rsquo;t respect you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading make sure to smash that like button and then go grab a beer, you&amp;rsquo;ve earned it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving screens is harder than I thought</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/leaving-screens-is-harder-than-i-thought/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 19:56:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/leaving-screens-is-harder-than-i-thought/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-phone-is-my-life&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;My phone is my life&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came across a post on &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;https://vaidik.bearblog.dev/feeling-uncomfortable-when-leaving-phone-at-home-shouldnt-be-normal/&#34;&gt;feeling uncomfortable leaving your phone at home&lt;/a&gt;. There are good reasons to bring a cell phone with you when going about daily life, such as emergencies and not getting bored while using the lavatory. But that doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily mean you ever need to &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; it, or even ever have it breathe fresh air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was sitting at the kitchen table yesterday evening when a &lt;a href=&#34;https://letsblurt.duckdns.org&#34;&gt;Blurt&lt;/a&gt; popped into my head and demanded to be written down. It said this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My phone is my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if this were Blurt the whole thing would have been truncated to &amp;ldquo;My phone is my&amp;rdquo; and so that&amp;rsquo;s why Blurt is stupid sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I sat there and stared at it for a minute or two. Pensively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-attention-whores-are-really-good-at-it&#34;&gt;The Attention-whores are really good at it.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last few days I&amp;rsquo;ve made an effort to not use my phone as much. Or any screens (with the caveat that my current occupation is listed as &amp;ldquo;web developer&amp;rdquo; or some such shit and so I need to use a computer for work). Let me re-phrase that to fit in with the cultural zeitgeist: I am trying to become more &lt;em&gt;mindful&lt;/em&gt; of my interactions with digital medias.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s harder than I thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s probably a combination of habit and whatever sordid psychology is used to keep people hooked, but it works. For the last few days, I&amp;rsquo;ve had this weird feeling of missing something. I want to say &amp;ldquo;not in a fear-of-missing-out way, but maybe that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what it is. It&amp;rsquo;s taking a fair amount of will-power and planning to stick to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conversely&#34;&gt;Conversely&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also felt more productive, because it&amp;rsquo;s nice outside and I&amp;rsquo;m not just spending my time looking at pictures of pro mountain bikers on Instantgram or whatever the hell else I end up doing on that thing. Even just a few minutes here and there where I have my head up and in the real world have been nicer, somehow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no real end-game here. I just like judging people who are walking around on their phones with their faces buried in their screens like assholes. Despite the fact that I generally don&amp;rsquo;t walk around with my phone (like an asshole), I am no better than them. And I &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; than &lt;em&gt;them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-news-oh-man&#34;&gt;The NEWS, oh man&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing that chewed through a lot of time and unnecessary mental energy is the news. I haven&amp;rsquo;t given up on the news completely, I have allowed myself to read &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com&#34;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; because it&amp;rsquo;s decently curated and only the bigger stories really ever filter through. Mostly it&amp;rsquo;s a bunch of nerdy headlines that I don&amp;rsquo;t actually understand, but when I say them at parties people nod along and look impressed. Oh and we watch Colbert&amp;rsquo;s monolog after dins regularly, so we get some real-hard-left news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading the news daily was a huge waste, for me personally. I don&amp;rsquo;t care if anyone else wants to read the news, it&amp;rsquo;s a free country. But it was like Faishbook, once I stopped using it I really didn&amp;rsquo;t miss anything there. I&amp;rsquo;m not even an anti-media nutjob, there&amp;rsquo;s just about 95% of things that happen every day will not affect me. So why expend the intellectual energy to learn about them or whatever emotional or psychological energy to empathize or what-have-you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what has happened since I quit reading the news:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The climate continues to go to shit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;American law/politics continues to be &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; stupid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vladdy Putin is doing some real awful stuff, poorly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Johnny Depp and some lady are in court and it&amp;rsquo;s stupid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There. You&amp;rsquo;re up-to-date. Call me cynical, you&amp;rsquo;re probably not far off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;its-summer&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s summer!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings me to the whole purpose of all of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers were supposed to make life better and they incredibly, totally have. However, they weren&amp;rsquo;t supposed to simultaneously turn us into mindless numbnutses who argue about everything and have really strong opinions about whatever the topic-du-jour is. They were supposed to provide us with more leisure time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s ride some bikes, hike some trails, pet some dogs, eat some veggie burgers. Plant some trees, eat some veggies and hummus and ride some more bikes. And then let&amp;rsquo;s hang out and talk about it without worrying about pictures to show off how good things are. Let&amp;rsquo;s just enjoy things as they happen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blurt Have I Become?</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/blurt-have-i-become/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 23:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/blurt-have-i-become/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-blurt-eat-blurt-world&#34;&gt;A blurt-eat-blurt world&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything truly great starts as a joke. Religion, capitalism, the movie Idiocracy. But then it rallies some support and just look where that&amp;rsquo;s gotten us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current highest-grossing side-project is called &lt;a href=&#34;https://letsblurt.duckdns.org&#34;&gt;Blurt&lt;/a&gt; (tied with all the others at $0). During a video by a youtube guy &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NYj3DnI81AQ&#34;&gt;Tom Scott&lt;/a&gt;, was going through some of his own historic predictions of what now would look like. He thought that blogging was going to remain big, which didn&amp;rsquo;t happen and was somewhat usurped by social media and &lt;em&gt;tweets&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a little bit &lt;em&gt;on the spectrum&lt;/em&gt; (probably), my brain continued the obvious trend: the future of tweets is bleak, and people will desire to communicate with even harsher character limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enter-blurt&#34;&gt;Enter Blurt&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My idea for project was to create the &lt;strong&gt;world&amp;rsquo;s first micro-tweeting platform called Blurt&lt;/strong&gt; (stylized &lt;strong&gt;BLURT&lt;/strong&gt; because onomatopoeia). You can write whatever you want, so long as it consists of 14 characters or less. But greater than 0 characters. It may not be the first, I didn&amp;rsquo;t do any market research in case I am wrong and can&amp;rsquo;t say that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It already exists and it is great. In case you haven&amp;rsquo;t tried it yet, &lt;a href=&#34;https://letsblurt.duckdns.org&#34;&gt;here is a link to Blurt&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m also proud of the fact that I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like dealing with login and user authentication and shit like that so I just didn&amp;rsquo;t bother with it. That&amp;rsquo;s right, you can impersonate others or log in as like twelve different users simultaneously. Or the same user twelve times. At this point I&amp;rsquo;m lucky no bots have discovered it, but also maybe bots are excited they haven&amp;rsquo;t discovered it because how much spam can you spam into 14 characters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-crowning-achievement&#34;&gt;The crowning achievement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone on blurt has that stupid &amp;ldquo;verified&amp;rdquo; checkmark after their name because we are an open and inclusive mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-yet&#34;&gt;And yet..&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few other features I want to add to blurt. I want to add infinite scroll, so that when you&amp;rsquo;re about to get to the end of the blurts, another batch load up. I want to have a &amp;ldquo;currently online&amp;rdquo; count, and be able to break that down into &amp;ldquo;socs&amp;rdquo; (pronounced like soashes, short for socials) and &amp;ldquo;jerks&amp;rdquo; where soashes are the cool people who post (go read &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Outsiders_(novel)&#34;&gt;The Outsiders&lt;/a&gt; or it won&amp;rsquo;t make sense and that&amp;rsquo;s on you) and jerks just lurk and don&amp;rsquo;t add to the cacaphony. You can&amp;rsquo;t spell cacaphony without caca unless you spell it correctly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also I need to make it more friendly to desktop users, since I made it originally with mobile in mind but I feel like it would be a fun thing to have up in a window behind all the work stuff I&amp;rsquo;m pretending to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if I&amp;rsquo;m going to do all this shit anyway, it turns out I&amp;rsquo;ll probably just start building it from the ground up again. Which isn&amp;rsquo;t nearly as daunting a task as I&amp;rsquo;m pretending it is since in its current state, Blurt literally took me two days to throw together, and also I wrote a bunch of other code for my daytime job during those two days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;quels-seront-les-changements&#34;&gt;Quels seront les changements?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site was originally an excuse to try to make something using an emerging web technology called &lt;a href=&#34;https://kit.svelte.dev/&#34;&gt;SvelteKit&lt;/a&gt;. I enjoyed monkeying with SvelteKit, but quickly learned that it was massively overpowered for my use-case. It&amp;rsquo;s more for making a full-fledged website, whereas Blurt could easily be accomplished using what us big nerds call a SPA, or a single-page application. It will seem like you are at the login page and then on the chatting page, but really they are the same page and the code just makes it look like there is a new URL, even though in reality you&amp;rsquo;re still on the same page but like, with a different background. Weird, eh? You probably use this type of stuff all the time without realizing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So SvelteKit is going to get put on the backburner, and will be supplanted with a FRONT-END which the user interacts with, and a BACK-END which is where the database lives and where all the big decisions are made (aka the business logic).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;front-end-stuff&#34;&gt;Front-End Stuff&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The front end stuff will be written in &lt;a href=&#34;https://svelte.dev/&#34;&gt;Svelte&lt;/a&gt; which is similar to SvelteKit but better for dealing with purely user-interface stuff. Anything the user deals with is user interface. So yay, you&amp;rsquo;ll get to see the end result of something written in Svelte! Also to make the page pretty I like to use a project called &lt;a href=&#34;https://tailwindcss.com/&#34;&gt;TailwindCSS&lt;/a&gt; because I don&amp;rsquo;t like using an extra file to tell the browser how to make everything look, which I&amp;rsquo;ve always begrudgingly accepted. But now everyone else has also decided we hate doing that so now we can stop!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;back-end-stuff&#34;&gt;Back-End Stuff&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to skip this part, but I am more excited about this than the front-end stuff. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to write for a general-audience instead of just dweeby code-nerds, so hopefully it makes some sense and may even offer you a window into wtf happens behind the curtain on websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now when Blurt loads the page containing blurts, it loads 250 of them. Then two seconds later, it checks again and downloads them again if they haven&amp;rsquo;t changed. If there has been a change, such as a new Blurt, it.. ..just downloads them again. Every two seconds. Forever. The browser makes a &lt;em&gt;request&lt;/em&gt; to my server, and the server sends the &lt;em&gt;response&lt;/em&gt; to the request. It&amp;rsquo;s a process called polling and it works fine for this purpose but it isn&amp;rsquo;t very elegant and I don&amp;rsquo;t love it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to make use of a technology called websockets. Intead of the request/response cycle, the browser and server make a connection and the connection is maintained between them. That way, instead of the constant request-response cycle, the server can just send a new blurt whenever someone else posts one! This wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible the way SvelteKit works, so I need to create a new server that will happily do websockets stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To write the new server, I will use a language called TypeScript. Most people have heard of Javascript, and it works great in a lot of cases. But there is a concept in computers called &amp;ldquo;typing&amp;rdquo;. &lt;em&gt;types some words&lt;/em&gt;. No but for real. Here&amp;rsquo;s the basic idea: the letter &amp;ldquo;c&amp;rdquo; is a character. That&amp;rsquo;s a type. The word &amp;ldquo;cat&amp;rdquo; is a string [of characters]. Strings are types too. There are lots of others and users will usually need to create custom types. In javascript I might write some code that sends a string somewhere else. But what if that code is only expecting a character and a string causes it to break? I&amp;rsquo;m boned! TypeScript is designed to make it so that can&amp;rsquo;t happen. If you write the code that sends a string to somewhere that is expecting a character, TypeScript will give you a stern look and a shaking head while pointing out the error of your ways. It&amp;rsquo;s like a safety net for people like me (and everyone else) who write sort-of pretty shitty code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-nutshell&#34;&gt;The nutshell&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In broad strokes, that&amp;rsquo;s it. Well, not totally. My database is almost as basic as possible, a little guy called sqlite (pronounced like &amp;ldquo;sequel-light&amp;rdquo;). It gets the job done for the like five users a day I get. To talk between the code and the database I have a little helper called &lt;a href=&#34;https://prisma.io&#34;&gt;prisma&lt;/a&gt; which I actually like more than I should for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When will this happen? I don&amp;rsquo;t entirely know. In my defense, I can&amp;rsquo;t really remember how to program a server like this, I haven&amp;rsquo;t really done it in a year or so. But luckily there&amp;rsquo;s a million youtube videos to steer me in the right direction. And I&amp;rsquo;ve never used TypeScript in a project before. I figure that to land a job, having a bit of experience with it will be looked at with a sly, knowing grin. Having said that, there&amp;rsquo;s no time like the present, so let&amp;rsquo;s say I start tomorrow night and try to have something together by the end of April? That&amp;rsquo;s a month. If the weather is good I might not do much, but I&amp;rsquo;ll try to put in some honest effort. mmmmkay?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I need to work on my definition of idiot</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/i-need-to-work-on-my-definition-of-idiot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 07:32:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/i-need-to-work-on-my-definition-of-idiot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;starting-a-blog-is-super-easy-right&#34;&gt;Starting a blog is super-easy. Right?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My original thought was to sit down and write an article on &amp;ldquo;how any idiot can start a blog using &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;. Hugo is a &lt;em&gt;static site generator&lt;/em&gt;, which means that I create all my blog posts and Hugo mushes them into a usable website like you are using right now. There is minimal interactivity and no database so I thought the whole thing should be pretty for anyone to jump into and use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other perk that drew me into Hugo was the these posts are all written using a format called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.markdownguide.org&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;. A file written in markdown is just a normal boring text file that uses various combinations of characters for formatting. The thought is that these files can be read in plaintext format (like if you opened it in Notepad) or if you opened it in a dedicated markdown editor, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://typora.io&#34;&gt;Typora&lt;/a&gt; or some online eitor. [Aside: I actually spent real money on Typora. It&amp;rsquo;s like if Word was stripped down to the functions you actually use.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as an example, here&amp;rsquo;s what a snippet of markdown might look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# This is the title of the page
## And this is a second-level header

I am some text! I can be *italic* or **bold**! You can also include [links to Blurt](https://letsblusrt.duckdns.org).
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not bad, hey? Even without much knowledge of markdown, you can hopefully get a sense of how it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;so-whats-the-problem&#34;&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s the problem?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that at some point along the way I went full-nerd and forgot what a normal computer user is like. I sit here typing this into &lt;a href=&#34;https://code.visualstudio.com&#34;&gt;VSCode&lt;/a&gt; my desktop computer where I can easily access my Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL2) or have two Raspberry Pi&amp;rsquo;s in the basement that I can SSH into for whatever reasons. Before your eyes glaze over and you leave this site never to return, that stuff wasn&amp;rsquo;t supposed to make sense to you &amp;ndash; and that&amp;rsquo;s the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was going to write that &amp;ldquo;any idiot could do it&amp;rdquo;, what I meant was &amp;ldquo;any idiot with a decent amount of experience using a command-line and who is happy to websearch the inevitable problem points can do it&amp;rdquo; and holy crap are those two statements ever not the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was hoping I could write out some quick instructions here so that maybe a couple of friends might start some blogs and we can be part of an online blog-gang and rove around intimidating other blog-gangs or blog-citizens and experimenting with Cryptocurrencies/Web3 (the smoking of the internet). So what I will do instead, is break things down into two groups. The first being a quick version of what I&amp;rsquo;m using so the bigger nerds out there have a starting point. The second will be for normies who just want to start writing without getting bogged down in frustration before giving up and using Facebook as their soapbox of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sup-nerds-normies-can-skip-to-the-next-section&#34;&gt;Sup, nerds? (normies can skip to the next section)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned multiple times like it was Crossfit or something, I am using Hugo to generate the site. The pros of using Hugo are the superfast build speeds and quick hot-reloads via websockets which allow for a quick and pretty great development experience. It&amp;rsquo;s also a single binary without dependencies so it should be a lot easier to maintain in the long run. The templating language could apparently use some work but I don&amp;rsquo;t have many downsides since I am using it for the simplest possible site. And that&amp;rsquo;s it, my database is folders of markdown files and my front-end is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/janraasch/hugo-bearblog&#34;&gt;Bearblog theme&lt;/a&gt; with a few tweaks to improve a11y. It&amp;rsquo;s great for this purpose, I even plan to use minimal images which is strange for me because I love images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once everything was in place, I pushed the code to a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jeffreycharters/sadspiders&#34;&gt;public Github repository&lt;/a&gt; since I don&amp;rsquo;t give two shits about security because what are people going to do, hack and leak my publically available blog posts? Have fun with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To publish the site I signed up for an account on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netlify.com&#34;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt;, said &amp;ldquo;use the repo at this address&amp;rdquo; and they said &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo; and like two minutes later I was live! They use webhooks or something so that every time I push new updates to Github, the new site is built within a couple of minutes and we&amp;rsquo;re off to the races! It&amp;rsquo;s pretty great since the whole point of &lt;strong&gt;sad spiders&lt;/strong&gt; was &amp;ldquo;simple as possible for minimal excuses&amp;rdquo;. I recommend this pipeline, I like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sup-other-nerds-yes-this-is-you-normie&#34;&gt;Sup, other nerds? (yes, this is you, normie)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now when I say &amp;ldquo;normie&amp;rdquo;, I don&amp;rsquo;t mean to be mean like I normally do. Just that you don&amp;rsquo;t feel like plodding through a whole ton of crap just to start a really basic blog, and I applaud you for your mature, informed decision. So what do you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered sending out a few links to various blogging platforms but I decided I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do that. I want to send you to &lt;a href=&#34;https://bearblog.dev&#34;&gt;Bear Blog&lt;/a&gt; because it&amp;rsquo;s as barebones as &lt;strong&gt;sad spiders&lt;/strong&gt; and that&amp;rsquo;s what I want from people. Content, not &lt;em&gt;zazz&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes &lt;em&gt;zazz&lt;/em&gt;, but not always &lt;em&gt;zazz&lt;/em&gt;. So get yourself on over there and sign up and let me know so I can add you to my as-yet-uncreated Friends page!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;up-and-at-them&#34;&gt;Up and at them&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m getting real sick of the normal internet. The articles are all interesting but after reading them I don&amp;rsquo;t feel any better. I would way rather read some BS that people I &lt;em&gt;actually know&lt;/em&gt; have written rather than some carefully crafted nonsense. It&amp;rsquo;s the same way I&amp;rsquo;d rather watch &lt;em&gt;Father Ted&lt;/em&gt; over &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes in media, the message is the message. Marshall McLuhan, you idiot.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>