<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bikes on sad spiders</title>
    <link>https://sadspiders.ca/blog/bikes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bikes on sad spiders</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-CA</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2022-2025, the spiders.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 19:14:26 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sadspiders.ca/blog/bikes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Training Update: April 2025</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/training-update-april-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2025 19:14:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/training-update-april-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;preamble&#34;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to update this for a while. But I&amp;rsquo;ve been training and whatnot. So I never wrote a blog entries about how training has been going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The race is in 6 days. I have begun my taper period where the volume of training (but not intensity) is diminished. This should result in my maintaining fitness but allowing my body to fully recover so that by race day I&amp;rsquo;m all fired up and ready to haul ass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-things-have-been-since-february-of-this-year&#34;&gt;How things have been since February of this year&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nuts to that lets go back to December. I&amp;rsquo;ve screen-grabbed from &lt;a href=&#34;https://intervals.icu&#34;&gt;intervals.icu&lt;/a&gt; a visual representation of my training load since December, when I started training for this year&amp;rsquo;s Paris to Ancaster race:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./fitness.png&#34; alt=&#34;a figure showing the fitness of the author increasing then somewhat leveling off since December 2024&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main thing that is of concern in this graph is the blue line, which is the long-term training load. When I began in December, that number was 9, which may in reality be a mild underestimated but close enough. In my last update at the start of February, it was 37. Today as I write this, it stands at 54, a slight decrease from its peak at 56. Woo! So what does that mean? Between the amount of time spent on the bike (volume), and the effort of each of those rides (intensity), my training load has increased a shit-ton since I started this season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example. In the winter, I rode 5 days a week, and the power profile of a workout looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./foundation_power.png&#34; alt=&#34;a power profile showing five intervals of six minutes each with average power of 166w per interval and heart rate around 140 bpm&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was of course the base phase, but I remember even during this time that my quad muscles were often tired and sore. Which was good, I feel like I built myself up in a decent amount of time instead of being ridiculous and being in a lot of pain or running out of gas and getting discouraged as I so often do. More recent rides have looked more like the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./recent_power.png&#34; alt=&#34;a power profile with many intervals of varying duration and power levels&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a challenging-but-doable ride. I definitely came off the bike one hell of a lot sweatier than the ride in the previous image. But I would say my legs were no more sore than they were after the easier sessions. So, good! Training achieved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;that-blip-in-the-training-load-figure&#34;&gt;That blip in the training load figure?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work went haywire. Extra stress, extra brainpower. According to my Garmin watch, my heart rate variability (HRV) was showing that my stress wasn&amp;rsquo;t being managed well. I dread overtraining and/or burnout, so I hit the brakes for a while then just rested for five days, which is where the form line underneath that blue line briefly turns blue as well. That indicates my training status was &lt;em&gt;fresh&lt;/em&gt;. And what do you do when you&amp;rsquo;re fresh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FTP tests!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I was all fired up from having rested for a few days and decided to go hard. I put on Andrew WK&amp;rsquo;s masterpiece &amp;ldquo;I Get Wet&amp;rdquo; and set out to do a Zwift ramp test, which is a great way to overestimate FTP but this is the way I did my first test so may as well be consistent. Have a look:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./ramp_test.png&#34; alt=&#34;a bunch of squiggly lines from the ramp test. most important is the power profile which peaks at 360W for a few seconds&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the test starts with a warm-up, then you ride at 100 W for one minute. Then you ride at 120 W for one minute. And so on and so forth until you literally cannot push the pedals any further. At which point a little window pops up and says &amp;ldquo;you done?&amp;rdquo; and the acknowledgement says &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m Toast&amp;rdquo; which hopefully you feel honest in pressing in that moment. Then I forget but it&amp;rsquo;s something like 75% of your best minute of power is your FTP, which is kind of like weight in that its mainly an estimate and no one is entirely truthful about theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in December when I started, my FTP was clocked in at 225 W. According to this test on March 28, my FTP was estimated at 261 W! That&amp;rsquo;s a 16% improvement in four months, I&amp;rsquo;ll take it! However, my two other training programs (intervals.icu and Xert) both set my FTP at 250 W based on probably more realistic algorithms so I&amp;rsquo;ll use that. But still, yay me! I am actually a little amazed that effort and consistency actually make a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Downside: the difference between 225 W and 250 W is 11%, so all of my workouts just became 11% more difficult which actually kinda sucks shit for the first couple of weeks. And now we rinse and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more week of easier rides, it&amp;rsquo;s nice to look forward to summer. Not entirely sure what will happen after the race on Sunday. The local mountain bike trails should be thawed, so hopefully I am inspired to go out for lots of rides and enjoy the great outdoors. We&amp;rsquo;re probably going to sign up for another race in early June, so I don&amp;rsquo;t think that structured training will be too far away, but I also think it&amp;rsquo;s probably good to just ride to work and have some adventures and not just get weird about numbers. No orthotrainia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I&amp;rsquo;ve got all my nutrition sorted for the ride, hopefully my gear will be suitable for the myriad possible temperatures on race day. And really, I hope I have fun and have the mental clarity to enjoy race day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;denouement&#34;&gt;Denouement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am glad I purchased my trainer. It gave me something to think about over the winter, and has hopefully let me feel good about myself. I enjoy having these objective numbers that I can&amp;rsquo;t poo-poo when I am feeling dumpy. There&amp;rsquo;s hard evidence that fitness is improving, and that is good for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few more rides, lots of rest and hopefully some good healthy meals and it&amp;rsquo;s game on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Training Update: February 2025</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/training-update-feb-2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2025 15:29:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/training-update-feb-2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;preamble&#34;&gt;Preamble&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point last year like the dumbass that I am, I thought it would be a good idea to spend my wellness money from work on a pair of relatively cheap &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elite-wheels.com/product/elitewheels-drive-g45-ss-gravel-bike-carbon-wheels/&#34;&gt;aero rims&lt;/a&gt; from China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then I did some soul searching because I realized I was trying to throw money at riding faster. If you do a quick doodle search, you&amp;rsquo;ll quiclkly learn that getting aero rims is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cyclingnews.com/features/get-aero-for-less-we-rank-bike-upgrades-ranked-by-watts-saved-vs-cost/&#34;&gt;one of the most dogshit ways to spend your money to get faster&lt;/a&gt;. So there&amp;rsquo;s that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a bang-for-your-buck kind of guy. So I threw that plan into my mental recycle bin and hatched a new plan: I&amp;rsquo;m going to actually train and see if that can make me faster. So I bought a Wahoo Kickr Core smart trainer and here we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-things-started-december-2024&#34;&gt;How things started: December 2024&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hooked up the trainer and subscribed to Zwift and went and did an FTP test. FTP is functional threshold power, which is the estimated amount of power one can sustain for an hour and underscores a lot of what you do while training. My inital estimated FTP according to a Zwift ramp test was &lt;strong&gt;225 watts (W)&lt;/strong&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if this is good or bad. I feel like it should have been higher but that&amp;rsquo;s the number I am working with for now. The next day I do a benchmark ride and it seems right. Sorry, my pride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enroll in the FTP Builder workout on Zwift a 6-week set of workouts with about four or five sessions a week. I start training. I train good!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point I decide that if I&amp;rsquo;m going to be sitting in my basement for hours trying to be more fitter that it&amp;rsquo;s a good investment to get a &lt;a href=&#34;https://sadspiders.ca/bike-fit-grimey&#34;&gt;bike fit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can jump ahead to about January 18th, the end of the FTP Builder program. All is well, I am nervous about burning out but have been sensible about it and used &lt;a href=&#34;https://intervals.icu&#34;&gt;intervals.icu&lt;/a&gt; to track my recovery/form. My new FTP? Well, here&amp;rsquo;s the rub: &lt;em&gt;I never checked my FTP at the end of the FTP Builder&lt;/em&gt;. I know. I&amp;rsquo;m a bad content creator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So y I no check? I was looking at my options for the next level of my training. The most obvious was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trainerroad.com/&#34;&gt;TrainerRoad&lt;/a&gt;, but I ended up putting my trust into a more local choice - &lt;a href=&#34;https://xertonline.com&#34;&gt;Xert&lt;/a&gt;. This platform uses all the info from my trainer to determine that workouts that will help me reach my goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./intervals.png&#34; alt=&#34;a calendar showing a ride almost every day for the past two weeks&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having something give me options for workouts is nice because it makes it so there&amp;rsquo;s one less thing I have to think about and they have enough variety to keep me from getting overbored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-its-going&#34;&gt;How it&amp;rsquo;s going&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Xert has been providing a number of suggestions for workouts for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve gone from a weekly training stress score (a measure of how much training you&amp;rsquo;re doing) from 252 in early December to this week being 399. They provide a graph showing roughly this as the blue line on the following chart from intervals.icu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./fitness.png&#34; alt=&#34;a figure showing the fitness of the author increasing since December 2024&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignore the purple line which shows Fatigue (7 day weighted average of training load) but lets focus on the blue line which is Fitness (42-day weighted average of training load). It makes me happy and keeps me motivated for now to see that line going up and up. Apparently I&amp;rsquo;ve vastly increased my training load but I still feel about as tired as when I was much earlier on in the program: I may actually be getting more fit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The green line underneath is Form, which is Fitness minus Fatigure. The line being green is good, means I am increasing fitness at a sustainable level. Red is bad and risks burnout, grey is stagnation and means I am not improving. Once I am race-ready I will ramp down the training load which will increase that line hopefully into the &amp;ldquo;Fresh&amp;rdquo; blue category and my body will just be jonesing to give&amp;rsquo;er at that point. Neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;where-were-going-next&#34;&gt;Where we&amp;rsquo;re going next&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in plain english, I&amp;rsquo;m doing easy rides these days. Relatively so. I did a two hour ride this morning and was tired but still feeling quite good afterwards. A few hours later I did some weighted lunges and single-leg Romanian deadlifts and stuff to try to add a bit of extra strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Xert program I am currently using is event preparation. I told them about my target event (P2A at end of April) and it has set me up with a three phase program: Base-Build-Peak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I am nearing the end of the &lt;strong&gt;Base&lt;/strong&gt; phase of the program. This is ultimately the answer to why I didn&amp;rsquo;t do an FTP test. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit with my updated plan. The base phase is just adding a lot of training volume (time) without adding much intensity. My body making a bunch of new mitochondrias and getting good at turning glycogen into lactate and then turning the lactate back into glycogen. Training my quadriceps to recruit lots of muscle fibers in case some start to get tired.  Increase my red blood cells count so that I can move them oxygens through my bloodstream more easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up is the &lt;strong&gt;Build&lt;/strong&gt; phase, which starts around February 11, I think. I have a feeling that that&amp;rsquo;s where the suffering is going to increase substantially. The workouts will start adding much more high-intensity intervals to increase my VO2Max, the amount of oxygen my body can process and get to the muscles over a given time. But this comes at the expense of overriding the signals that my legs are sending that they&amp;rsquo;ve had enough. But hey, I guess that&amp;rsquo;s training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final phase is the &lt;strong&gt;Peak&lt;/strong&gt; phase. In my case as an amateur weekend warrior, this will involve more of an increase in training load and more specific intervals to really push the body to its limits before tapering before coming back stronger. I&amp;rsquo;m really going to be monitoring my form and recovery during this phase because this is where the risk of overtraining is real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;denouement&#34;&gt;Denouement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so good. Hopefully fitness is improving just by showing up for every session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motivation is still high, looking forward to the race. Not looking forward to more high-intensity intervals but yes interested to see what Xert estimates my FTP at once I get to that point.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grimey fits me now!</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/bike-fit-grimey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 17:38:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/bike-fit-grimey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I&amp;rsquo;ve started doing longer rides, I&amp;rsquo;ve always been fighting through some niggle or another. Well, that might not be entirely true. When I first got &lt;a href=&#34;./the-windiest-135km-bike-ride&#34;&gt;Grimey&lt;/a&gt; I had a Brooks leather saddle and it was comfortable as heck until I got rid of it because it was leather and my bike stuff needs to be able to get wet and muddy and love it and not need any coddling. So ever since then on long rides, my shoulders get sore and my trapeziuses get sore and my perineal area gets sore and so on and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;crushing-basement-kay-ems&#34;&gt;Crushing basement Kay-ems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of my newfound dream of getting a bit faster, I decided to lay out some self-improvement bucks and grab a WAHOO Kickr Core smart trainer and a subscription to Zwift. Sorry no affiliate link for trainer but hey get a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zwift.com/invite/JtsLTQfeEK&#34;&gt;free month of Zwift!&lt;/a&gt;. So now I get to ride Grimey all winter in the basement and also enjoy some crappy graphics. Thanks, Zwift!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./zwift-setup.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Towel, water, fan, dog. Ready to virtual ride&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So at some point last year I decided that a good way to get faster was to &lt;em&gt;throw money at the problem&lt;/em&gt; which is always a good thing to try. It keeps the economy going which is very, very important to consider when doing literally anything. But then at some point I realized: that&amp;rsquo;s stupid! I was trying to buy my way to faster when what I should have been doing was &lt;em&gt;buying myself faster but in a different way&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some serious soul searching I realized that it&amp;rsquo;s not Grimey&amp;rsquo;s fault that I&amp;rsquo;m not riding Grimey faster. It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;my&lt;/strong&gt; fault and I need to start taking some responsibility for my actions. DAMN IT, I hate taking responsibility for my actions. So I got the trainer and all that and resolved to open up the new year by finally spending some of the Wellness Money from my benefits plan to get a professional bike fit from the Local Bike Shop. I was hesitant. What can this idiot know that twenty minutes of youtube videos can&amp;rsquo;t teach you? Well, a lot as it turns out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-knocked-down-a-few-pegs&#34;&gt;Getting knocked down a few pegs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, my bike is the right size for me. You hear that, Grimey? They&amp;rsquo;re not going to force us apart! However, over the two hours that Tim the Bike Fitter and I spent together, there were a number of changes to help improve my situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My arches are high! Need to add some fresh insoles to support those things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Based on the insoles removed from the shoes, all of the pressure was on the ball of the foot right behind the big toe. This is less than ideal! Spread the power across the entire pedal spindle. This should help to align the leg from hip to toe and decrease injury likliehood. This is something for me to consciously work on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I ride in a toe-down style. This is less than ideal for power transfer and biomechanics. Now I need to also work on keeping my heel down throughout the pedal stroke. Hold on, I need to write this down.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spread power across all metatarsals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep heel down while pedalling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So wait, is there a reason why I pedal in that way? Oh, my hamstrings are tight as heck. So now I get some exercises to do to lengthen and strengthen the backside of my lower body. Romanian deadlifts and glute bridges. Yay, homework!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh and also as a result of tight hamstrings I am also rounding my back to give them a little extra space. Also because I have bad posture in general like literally everyone else.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep a neutral spine while riding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I complained of pain in the perineal area, which is more commonly known by another more crass name. Anyway, I don&amp;rsquo;t sit far enough back on the seat. Like an asshole! So I need to make sure I sit further back on the seat as well. This should help keep the pressure on the sit bones and not the soft fleshy perineal area. We leaned the seat forward a couple of degrees as well. I think at some point I tipped it back to try to not slide forward but clearly that didn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handlebars rotated forwards but brifters rotated towards me and also angled inwards. This allows a more full grip to distribute pressure across the hands and anglaed inwards to increase aero and maybe also comfort.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also we replaced my ten-years-of-riding cleats which it turns out has a massive difference. New cleats just lock you right down to the pedals. I like it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;before-and-afters&#34;&gt;Before and afters!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, words are stupid. Lets just have a look at the before picture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./chartersprefit.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A profile picture of the author on his bike with a rounded back, awkward arm position and pointed toes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So obviously I look like a hack and that if I&amp;rsquo;m ever able to ride more than 50 feet without falling off it&amp;rsquo;d be a miracle. Well, maybe it just looks uncomfortable for more than an hour of riding at a time. Okay so now let&amp;rsquo;s compare with the after:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./charterspostfit.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A profile picture of the author on his bike with near perfect form after fitting&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay yeah it looks the exact same to most people. So here&amp;rsquo;s a flip-flop of before and after:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./animation.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Animation of the two previous pictures making differences more obvious&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See?! You can also see we made the stem more longer (part that holds handlebars).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;verdict&#34;&gt;Verdict?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like it! I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing my exercises and trying to be disciplined about spreading out power across the spindle, keep my heel low, keeping a neutral spine and getting my ass back on the seat. I&amp;rsquo;ve done a two hour ride on an indoor trainer and it was not awful! Sure I had to stand a couple of times to relieve some pressure spots but nothing major. So yes, given that I had a few bucks that I was able to spend on it, I am glad to have made this investment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Riding indoors is a great way to keep fit in the winter. If increasing comfort and minimizing injuries will help make it less awful, I&amp;rsquo;m all for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bike fits = good. Not like Bike Rage fits, but this kind.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Race Report: Paris to Ancaster 2024</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/paris-ancaster-2024/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 17:38:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/paris-ancaster-2024/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Paris-Ancaster bike race is a multi-surface event with a variety of distances that occurs each year in the spring. We – myself and my friend Michael – chose the 68 km distance. He wants to do the race as a birthday gift to himself. I sign on because I have no good reason not to. Let&amp;rsquo;s just get right into this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gearing-up&#34;&gt;Gearing Up&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weather report heading towards race day started narrowing in on unseasonable warmth and humidity, also possibly rain but maybe not rain. I hum and hah about what to wear. In the end I throw a variety of crap into a bag and I can make my decision at the last minute based on how things feel at the start gate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my own records, I put a 60mm stem onto Grimey (from 90mm?) to reduce the reach which I think increased comfort. Maybe end up with 70mm but an improvement for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-training&#34;&gt;On Training&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From sometime in the winter until race day, I did a decent number of multi-hour zone 2 rides throughout the late-winter. I had some other stressful stuff happening in the background so I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to do as much intense training (HIIT) as I&amp;rsquo;d hoped. &lt;em&gt;Note for next year:&lt;/em&gt; Do waytf more HIIT. Whether it be hills or just timed higher-intensity stretches of rail trail, need to deffo up the intensity. Why? Because riding three hours at above-training-level pace is less than ideal. Will hopefully be able to carry more base load into the winter this year so that we can come out swinging next spring. Also note: pistol squats, plyo leg stuff. Get strong AF. Which is for me at least a little bit strong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;on-the-bike&#34;&gt;On the bike&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my own future reference, and I must insist that I am not proud of my setup, here is some the crap I had hanging off my ride and can be seen in the photos below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ass Savers Win Wing&lt;/strong&gt; (road width) fender on the back wheel. I liked not having the skunk-stripe and coldness up my ass and it never seemed to get clogged or anything. Might work again in the future, probably worth investing in the wider gravel variant. And shit, maybe even a &lt;strong&gt;classic-style Ass Saver&lt;/strong&gt; would be suffish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ass savers mini-mudder&lt;/strong&gt; front mud guard. This thing clogged up like 9 times once we got into the thick tacky mud. It can go to hell. Commuting yes, &lt;strong&gt;racing hell no.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apidura seat bag:&lt;/strong&gt; I don&amp;rsquo;t think I ever pulled anything out of this, was probably just a weight penalty with no real gain. However it&amp;rsquo;s also actually very light, so it might be worth including a few tools and pump and crap in there but keep it as light as possible. There&amp;rsquo;s about a 0% chance you&amp;rsquo;re going to pull over and get something out of this bag or add to it unless absolutely necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apidura stem bag:&lt;/strong&gt; this is where the magic should be stored, but maybe need to find a way to organize shit better. First, don&amp;rsquo;t bring apple cinammon energy bars. I love apple cinammon energy bars, but you don&amp;rsquo;t feel like trying to chow down on them when your heart rate isn&amp;rsquo;t dropping below 160bpm and you don&amp;rsquo;t want some lycra-clad superChad to blast past you while you waste your energy on not choking today (which is actually a great use of energy). &lt;em&gt;Bring gels instead.&lt;/em&gt; Like &lt;em&gt;so many&lt;/em&gt; gels. Cram your water bottles full of gatorade. Carbs! Always carbs! Just keep a ton of sugar in this thing. Maybe even just cram the phone in here too. I had it in a jersey pocket and it was fine but got pretty gritty and scraped off a bunch of finish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I ran a pair of 35mm width &lt;strong&gt;Schwalbe G One RS tires.&lt;/strong&gt; Although these are great tires, I feel like something like my stock 40mm Maxxis Rambler might offer a little bit more grip and float in the muddier sections without adding much rolling resistance in the tarmac and gravel sections. Something to consider moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;race-day&#34;&gt;Race Day!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got surprisingly decent sleep the night before the race, and was up pretty early to finalize prep before Andrew, my chuffeur-and-photographer for the day, came by. Weather radar looks like rain will be likely, settle on wearing a normal short-sleeve jersey with a rain jacket over top. Also jeans. Yeah jeans. I just can&amp;rsquo;t do lycra. I &lt;em&gt;won&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; do lycra. I will end up being refered to as &amp;ldquo;jeans guy&amp;rdquo; by a number of fellow riders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some stupid reason there is an officer blocking the route to the venue, so we double back and try another route. It gets us closer but we encounter more closed roads. We make the decision for me to ride the final 2km to the venue and Andrew would toddle off to scout his locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./01-shoes-on.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Getting them shoes done up&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./02-before-shot.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;K let&amp;rsquo;s go&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find Michael in the parking lot-slash-quarry where the race starts, strap my plate to the handlebars and do some quick warm up spins. I&amp;rsquo;m nervous but no one really seems to give a crap that I exist. A light rain falls as we start getting into the right corral for our start. Thinking positive though! I like rain, this will play to my benefit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;race-start&#34;&gt;Race Start!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we&amp;rsquo;re in the start corral, I think we&amp;rsquo;re at the back of &lt;strong&gt;Wave 2&lt;/strong&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of people around wearing team kit, making me feel inadequate for sure in my jeans. Oh well, I hopefully have got this and won&amp;rsquo;t somewhow embarass myself over the next few hours. As the time ticks down, everyone looks around nervously. Once the first wave is gone, we move up to fill the void they&amp;rsquo;ve left. I question my decisions leading up to this point. I remind myself that I&amp;rsquo;m just going to race my race and not get caught up with everyone else and going too hard out of the gate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as the start gun goes off to set us loose on the course, I abandon my resolve to race my own race. This pack of several hundred people set off and the speed is hard to resist. Michael and I are separated very early on. I see him a few riders ahead of me and step on the gas to catch up. He&amp;rsquo;s a group of riders ahead of me. We go through a farmer&amp;rsquo;s field, through some real muddy bits and he&amp;rsquo;s gone. I think he&amp;rsquo;s ahead of me so I jam on the gas again to find him. I stay on the gas. I am flying but also I am dying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point we get onto some tarmac and I can see from the riders ahead that we&amp;rsquo;ve got at least a couple of km to catch him. I abandon my plan to not make any stupid moves and make solo unprotected attacks through open country. I do not catch Michael. I have no idea where he is. Aside from the hundreds of other riders and the police and volunteers and family members at every junction, I am utterly alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./03-bridgerton.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The author slightly muddied after passing beneath a train bridge&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./04-tarmac.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Just out for a gentle bike ride on a country road&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My anxiety ebbs and flows throughout this process. I enjoy riding along country roads, I take time to enjoy the surroundings, have some friendly chats with fellow competitors. I get many jeans related comments, I am Jeans Guy. Standouts included &amp;ldquo;messenger-style, right on&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;jeans? you fucking psycho!&amp;rdquo;. Many ask me if they are jeans or fake jeans. I tell them the are Du/er jeans. Many people add that they love their Du/er jeans. I make new plans to become the Du/er jeans sponsored guy and try to live off of $5k a year plus race entry fees. I never follow through, another squandered opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;feed-zone-number-one&#34;&gt;Feed Zone Number One&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point after biking and biking and biking I arrive at the first feed zone, wondering if Michael would be waiting for me. He is not! I must have passed him in all the commotion. I am so fast. I am a great guy at racing bikes. I also feel like I am going to throw up, I am absolutely gased already and am not used to cramming calories down my throat at this pace. I take a couple of minutes to let a wave of panic subside and grab an apple to try to keep things moving. Top up water bottles with the sponsor&amp;rsquo;s suger water. Where the shit is Michael? A lot of people are going by. Do I abandon him? I get a text from home - &amp;ldquo;everything okay?&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;Just at feed stop, going to wait a few more minutes for Michael&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no way I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; far ahead of him. Michael&amp;rsquo;s a few years older than me, but he trained a lot for this race. It becomes more and more obvious that despite this pace, he must be ahead of me. And at this point, un-catch-uppably far ahead of me. Alright, off we go. How long have I been waiting? Ten minutes? More? Oh well, let&amp;rsquo;s get going, and from now on it&amp;rsquo;s every man for himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We head out from the feed zone and into a horribly muddy little section. People are hopping off their bikes and running down the hill. The guy directly in front of me suddenly loses all traction and I have to semi-bail and skip along awkwardly to avoid damging his internal organs. Am I actually having fun?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./05-447-so-tiny.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I am huge compared to some people&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mud-so-much-mud&#34;&gt;Mud. So much mud.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point we veer off the dirt road we are on and it&amp;rsquo;s just a mudfest. Deep, tacky, sticky. It grabs onto my tires and doesn&amp;rsquo;t let go. Trying to force my way through mud with a brick of compacted mud and leaves through my front fender spike my heart rate to 186bpm, my highest throughout the entire race. People are piling up behind me. I ride off to the edge of the cource and empty out the leaves. I am angry at my fender. It was supposed to help, not hinder! I get it cleared, I head back out. There is nothing but time to be made in this section. These are mostly &lt;em&gt;roadies&lt;/em&gt;. Roadies have the most dogshit bike handling skills and can&amp;rsquo;t ride singletrack to save their stupid little lives (aside: I&amp;rsquo;m fine with roadies, I just get weirdly competitive sometimes. I don&amp;rsquo;t like Lycra though). But still I lost time because of my narrow tire choice and my stupid fender. &lt;strong&gt;Note for next year:&lt;/strong&gt; no front mud guard. Wider tires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The miles tick by. I settle into a nice rhythm. There is a lady who is going exactly the speed I want to go, which is slightly faster than my body would like to go. I stick to her back wheel. We exchange occasional words. We&amp;rsquo;re starting to get tired. Everyone&amp;rsquo;s pace has slowed. The 30kmh+ pace is a meager 25kmh. Some folks are able to keep up, but others are hitting the limits of their energy reserves and are noticeably struggling. I might be one of those people, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure. I am focusing on being okay. I am going to be okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;feed-zone-number-two&#34;&gt;Feed Zone Number Two&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blasted past it hardly even realized it was there, having a chat with some dude on the rail trail. Definitely no Michael.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-tail-end-of-the-trail&#34;&gt;The tail end of the trail&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last while on the trail is a bit unreal. A great long ride along some rail trail, Michael&amp;rsquo;s training grounds. Getting towards the end of the course there is a really long and muddy downhill section, affectionately named the Mudslide of Death. A great many riders, both semi-exhausted and out of breath and of dubious bike-handling skills are jumping off their bikes and running down the mudslide. I am much more stupboarn. I will ride Grimey down the mudslide of death or we will be pitched into the adjacent forest together to think about the choices that have brought us to this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./05.5-railtrail.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Out of the frying pan, dot dot dot&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./06-mudslide.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jeffrey enjoying his mudslide of death&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now here&amp;rsquo;s the weird thing. Despite having had borderline low blood sugar for an hour, having brakes that at this point have been ground down to nothing by the constant assault of gritty mud, I am somehow able to look like this is the best I have ever felt in my entire life. Get a load of this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./07-peak-jeff.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The author seems to be enjoying his bike ride, despite all indicators to the contrary&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My feet are so muddy that the poor velcro on my ancient shoes has given up. There&amp;rsquo;s chunks of mud hanging off from the bottom of my shoes or pedals or something. If you look closely you can see I am heading down a gentle incline &lt;em&gt;with my brakes fully engaged&lt;/em&gt; since that doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually do anything anymore. My hairy calfs are carrying an extra half-pound of mud per side. Grimey is carrying another pound on various horizontal ledges. I&amp;rsquo;ve eaten enough dirt that my teeth have that after-dentist polished feel. And yet I am clearly having the greatest time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for those who must know, the thing sticking up from my back is either a paint stirrer stick for knocking mud off the bike, or an Ass Savers Speed Mullet I foolishly thought I might attach at some point to keep my feets clean. Ha ha ha yeah right. How young and naive I was!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But despite what you see, I felt like hell. But we&amp;rsquo;re getting close to the end! There&amp;rsquo;s just that one big climb that everyone has warned me is awful. And my quads have begun to spasm if I stand and pedal. Stupid legs. But I will prevail!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final climb is where I get my heart to its second-highest peak at a mere 183bpm. I try to finish strong. I run out of gas halfway up the hill. I tried to force my way up, mind you. At some point I was straining and closed my eyes and felt some sort of weird flash or something like something broke in my brain so I took 30 seconds to just stop and collect myself. I can hear the crowd cheering up ahead. I will finish strong. I start pedalling, get some momentum and am able to force the pedals to spin to the top of the hill. And just like that, it&amp;rsquo;s all over. I swear that this sucks so much and I will never do it again. But I&amp;rsquo;ve reached my goal of completing the race. Yay me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./08-finish.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Jeffrey crossing the finish line not in last place&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;denouement&#34;&gt;Denouement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I caught up with Andrew who curses himself to have missed me making my way across the finish line. That&amp;rsquo;s okay. We find Michael. Michael kicked my ass. I am happy for Michael. Because I know that next year when we do the race, I will crush him. And just like that, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that I will in fact do the race next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bikes get washed, food gets eaten and life goes on. It was a good time. I&amp;rsquo;m not a people person but I still enjoyed it all when I could and I retain fond memories already. I&amp;rsquo;ve already begun making notes on things I did right, things I did poorly and how to improve things for next year. And you&amp;rsquo;ve just read most of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time, keep fit and have fun. Bodybreak!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah the jeans were fine. Du/er nails it. Even wet, no problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ride Review: My first century</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/ride-review-my-first-century/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 19:56:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/ride-review-my-first-century/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s October! I&amp;rsquo;d been planning to ride 161km at some point this year and time was winding down, so this past Saturday was it. So I chucked some shit in my bike bags, chucked some albums onto a playlist and woke up early the Saturday of [Canadian] Thanksgiving weekend to see if I could do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./01-depart.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Grimey, my bike, all loaded up and ready for a shreddy.&#34;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
[Grimey all loaded up! I had taken the fenders off at one point and luckily reinstalled them the night before the ride.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;first-bit&#34;&gt;First bit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first bit was quite pleasant. The playlist started out with &lt;em&gt;Bleed American&lt;/em&gt; by Jimmy Eat World, an album I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to at least a thousand times before. It was nice cruising out of the neighbourhood at dawn, before anyone is out trying to hit me with their cars. I made it to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kissingbridgetrailway.ca&#34;&gt;Kissing Bridge Trail&lt;/a&gt;, an old rail trail near here, in just under half an hour. I&amp;rsquo;ve ridden along that stretch a bunch of times and this was about exactly the pace I was hoping for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scooted along the kissing bridge for not too many kilometers before it&amp;rsquo;s time to break north and head toward Fergus along some country roads. The second album probably kicks in somewhere along here, Anberlin&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Lost Songs&lt;/em&gt; album. I really like most of their albums, this one was specfically chosen to remind me to calm the eff down. I have a tendency to push the pace and rush through things, needed a reminder that this is a marathon, not a sprint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./02-light.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;My shadow on across the road in the foreground, some nice autumnal colour in the distance past a field.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part of the ride is nice and boring. These roads were part of a number of training rides so they&amp;rsquo;re kinda boring, despite being a nice place to watch the sun rise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;some-hints-of-whats-yet-to-come&#34;&gt;Some hints of what&amp;rsquo;s yet to come&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably listening to Small Brown Bike&amp;rsquo;s album &lt;em&gt;Our Own Wars&lt;/em&gt;. This was a bit of an impulse addition to the playlist. This album has seen regular rotation over the years, but never super high up on the list. However, maybe because the band has bike in the title, I&amp;rsquo;ve always enjoyed this album. Maybe one you just need to be in the mood for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./03-tree-tunnel.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A tunnel created by trees growing over a trail in full autumn colours.&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a pit stop at the local Tim Horton&amp;rsquo;s for a double-chocolate doughnut, I&amp;rsquo;m on my way on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://trailway.org&#34;&gt;Elora-Cataract Trailway&lt;/a&gt; out of Fergus. Had a chat with an older fella on an electric tricyle, thinking how nice it is that technology can help people have the wind blow through their hair who may not do so otherwise. Wish him Happy Thanksgiving as I say goodbye and blast ahead of him. A few seconds pass before he must suddenly realize it&amp;rsquo;s Thanksgiving weekend. &amp;ldquo;Happy Thanksgiving!&amp;rdquo; I hear in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also the sun has retreated behind some clouds. A lot of clouds. Not theatening rain, but definitely letting me know the expected 60% chance of rain will probably yield fruit. Menacing clouds. I shake my fist at them and carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./04-bridge.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Grimey leaning on a barrier in front of a bridge under a lot of construction&#34;&gt;
[I couldn&amp;rsquo;t tell from the internet whether or not this bridge was going to be passable, some things seemed yes and others seemed no. It turns out they were both right, depending on how you feel about climbing over stuff and trying to set your bike down gently from eight feet above the ground while wearing bike shoes.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The album &lt;em&gt;Wake the Dead&lt;/em&gt; by the Comeback Kids comes and goes. It&amp;rsquo;s a really great album if you like Hardcore. There&amp;rsquo;s also &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6DFKjZ_vuBk&#34;&gt;an amazing fan video&lt;/a&gt; on youtube and it makes me really miss being young and idiot. There&amp;rsquo;s some good singalongs here and I&amp;rsquo;m starting to get this impression this ride is going to fucking suck so the music helps a bit with morale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point I&amp;rsquo;m headed north towards a &lt;a href=&#34;https://trailerpark.fandom.com/wiki/We_Can%27t_Call_People_Without_Wings_Angels_So_We_Call_Them_Friends_(Episode)&#34;&gt;friend&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; place near Kenilworth. Out in the middle of all the fields, a crosswind has picked up. There&amp;rsquo;s a ton of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wind_fetch&#34;&gt;fetch&lt;/a&gt; so the wind is sustained from the west, and I know that once I leave her place, there&amp;rsquo;s about 50 kilometers of riding directly into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;lets-get-some-apples-russet-apples&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s get some apples! RUSSET APPLES!&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I cruise along enjoying &lt;em&gt;Something to Write Home About&lt;/em&gt; by The Get Up Kids, I get my first taste of riding directly west. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a bummer because the wind is doing a number on the quality of the audio through my wired ear buds. Lots of wind noise, so a lot of the songs I&amp;rsquo;m only hearing by singing along with them. Noiselessly. So I am silently listening to this album in two different ways at once. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit less than ideal, but I&amp;rsquo;m already trying to decide what I&amp;rsquo;m going to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I roll into our friend&amp;rsquo;s place sometime after 10am around the 65km mark. Despite living in Canada for over twenty years, she is still super-British and drinking a spot of tea and wearing a Bletchley Park t-shirt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She is a gracious hostess and takes me out to the RUSSET APPLE TREE to pick a few apples to help me on my way. So good! If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with this variety, you need to seek them out and try them since they are absolutely the best variety. While I&amp;rsquo;m here I may as well get the egg mcmuffin I brought into me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./05-apples.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Grimey being engulfed by a RUSSET APPLE TREE! omgz&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking stock, I&amp;rsquo;m feeling pretty good. 95 kilometers to go but I know that the next 50 are going to be a slog and that means knocking my speed down to like 15km/h and taking three stupid hours just to get two hours worth of far. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit demoralizing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hell, we&amp;rsquo;re here now and I&amp;rsquo;ve done a bunch of training so let&amp;rsquo;s just suck it up and keep moving forwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also I petted Clare&amp;rsquo;s dogs and waved at her cows so that improved morale briefly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./06-mooers.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Clare&amp;rsquo;s cows&#34;&gt;
[Bye cows, I love you!]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;wind-sounds&#34;&gt;*WIND SOUNDS*&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really excited to be listening to Ephilexia&amp;rsquo;s album &lt;em&gt;Sun, Please, Explode&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s math-rock and post-rock together! This means that it&amp;rsquo;s instrumental and mellow but technically so. You just have to try it. Just set like an hour aside with some really good sound system and just &lt;a href=&#34;https://inv.tux.pizza/watch?v=iEb8j-5IXAU&#34;&gt;listen to it&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe also smoke weed if that&amp;rsquo;s what you do or enjoy a small two fingers of Northern Harvest Rye Whiskey if you&amp;rsquo;re like me, and just be like &amp;ldquo;shit, he&amp;rsquo;s right, this is awesome&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So heading straight into the wind for the indefinite future. Riding into the wind super-sucks ass because it takes a lot of effort to get nowhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to keep going for three or more straight hours directly into the stupid wind. Occasionally there would be a short stretch of a couple of kilometers where the road would be headed north or south, and it was much easier going. This is pretty much the only thing that kept me going. To know that it might eventually not be terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./07-best.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Grimey in the middle of a road in the middle of fucking nowhere&#34;&gt;
[This is honestly the greatest moment of the whole ride. A single-lane gravel road, nobody around for miles &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; some sun!]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, at some point Ephilexia faded into &lt;em&gt;Exile in Oblivion&lt;/em&gt; by Strung Out. It turns out I sing along with everything while I am biking. Not actually singing, just mouthing the words like a constant, silent karaoke. This was a great album for this point in the ride. High-energy and just good songs. I must have planned for a higher-energy section here, since the next two albums are Much the Same&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Everything is Fine&lt;/em&gt; and Face to Face&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t Turn Away&lt;/em&gt; (the first punk tape I ever bought). Both skate-punk, both just full of songs I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to dozens of times and super easy to digest. For me, these albums are like arrowroot cookies for my brain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-hydrologic-cycle&#34;&gt;The hydrologic cycle&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere during this sufferfest, as I was being chased (coincidentally) by a gang of amish in a horse-drawn cart, I could see those clouds in the distance with the swaths of rain hanging down. I&amp;rsquo;m gonna get wet. In retrospect, I should have put on some Andrew WK but life&amp;rsquo;s not perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first rain wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bad. About half an hour of on-and-off drizzle. Not enough to actually soak through. I start to wonder just how cold I&amp;rsquo;ll be if I do indeed get soaked. I&amp;rsquo;ve got on a jacket and gloves but it&amp;rsquo;s 12C out and windy and I&amp;rsquo;m not really set up to be soaking wet. &lt;em&gt;Tant pis&lt;/em&gt;, nothing I can do about it anyway!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./08-rain.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Bike computer speckled with raindrops showing 103.74km, a nice rail-trail in the background&#34;&gt;
[The odometer has rolled over the 100km mark. Somewhere just north of Palmerston, Ontario.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point I finally get to the goddam Malcolm Line, the start of my road north, wind from the side instead of front. It&amp;rsquo;s so good. But I&amp;rsquo;m definitely getting tired. My arse hurts. My deltoids are sore. My wrists are sore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a whiny son of a bitch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But onwards we march! Not because it was easy, but because we thought it would be easy. I got a good quote from a friend after I told him I went ahead with the ride and actually completed it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the weather en route was anything like it is here, I&amp;rsquo;m truly sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But life is good! We&amp;rsquo;re headed north, there&amp;rsquo;s a measly 50km left to go. I can do 50km on Grimeyback in my sleep. Oh, Grimey is my bike&amp;rsquo;s name. I named him after Grimey from the Simpsons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./grimey.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Frank Grimes&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music has toned it down a little bit and I got through Still Mountain&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Artemis&lt;/em&gt;. A very mellow, gentle album. After this came Saosin&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Translating the Name EP&lt;/em&gt; which is like some sort of emo/screamo thing that I really enjoy. It&amp;rsquo;s got some really awesome spastic drumming and is worth a listen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./09-chips.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A wet and bepuddled road&#34;&gt;
[There&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;https://inv.tux.pizza/watch?v=jlzEjXu6QGQ&#34;&gt;line from the Simpsons&lt;/a&gt; that kept going through my head at this point: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I just wish I was home with a big bag of potatuh chips. Mmm, potatuh chips.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; The odometer is at 121km maybe?]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the way up Malcolm Line it rained twice more for ten or so minutes at a time. The final great landmark was getting to the rail trail which would take me from near Clifford all the way to my final destination. Super satisfying! I&amp;rsquo;m going to make it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;epic-conditions-for-an-epic-ride&#34;&gt;Epic conditions for an epic ride&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within about 5 minutes of getting on this trail the heavens decided it was time to test my tenacity and just really open up. Not torrential, but downpour for sure. And for good measure, the maintenance on the first half of the rail trail was sub-par and was basically just a trillion puddles linked together. So it was bumpy and wet. Fender helped &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;, but they don&amp;rsquo;t protect from water coming down from above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./10-trail.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The final rail trail!&#34;&gt;
[No more photos from the last couple of hours since it was cold out and also raining and my gloves were thoroughly soaked and if I took them off they&amp;rsquo;d never go back on and my fingies would get cold.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured by this point on the ride my brain would be a white paste and so threw some more post-rock on there. The eponymous [self-titled] album by &lt;em&gt;Transatlantic Alliance&lt;/em&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s this one track on this album that stands out to me called &lt;em&gt;Stay Inside&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s got a sample of an interview with a (possibly homeless) gentleman about how his life has just been a pile of shit and he just wants things to be better and he&amp;rsquo;s doing his best and life just sucks. Of course I know that I&amp;rsquo;ve had things way better than this guy, but I feel like it sands down some rough edges. To hear this guy who&amp;rsquo;s had a really rough life just wishing it was better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s weird to feel like the finish line is in sight and still have a couple of hours ahead of you, and knowing your going to have to get through it soaking effing wet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a glimmer of hope: Mildmay, Ontario. They&amp;rsquo;ve got a gas station and I shimmy in there and grab myself a bottle of Brand-name cola beverage! I&amp;rsquo;ve got an hour left, this can carry me across that finish line, rain be damned!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Editor&amp;rsquo;s note: I definitely got some looks during that stop.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ration the cola beverage over the next hour. A good swig every fifteen minutes. Keep my energy up and something to break up the last segments. The last album to come on is &lt;em&gt;Stay What You Are&lt;/em&gt; by Saves the Day, another old emo record from the early noughts. Another album I can just mumble along with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;then-it-was-just-done&#34;&gt;Then it was just done&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kept plowing along, finally there were ten km left, then five. Then the farm was in sight. The last five km or so I put it into cooldown mode, put it into an easier gear and just spin the legs out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then along the last stretch the odometer pulls across the 161km and I&amp;rsquo;ve done it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I expected. A feeling of elation. Some sort of connection with a higher power. The other problems in my life melting away and having no more significance because I did something challenging and achieved what I set out to do. I overcame adversity!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, some cars flew past me and the odometer eventually ticked to 162km and on I went. It was only a couple more to the farm anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pulled into the driveway and Ashley asked if I wanted the dogs out. I said &amp;ldquo;nah thanks&amp;rdquo; because it was still all wet and rainy and they&amp;rsquo;d just get all wet and muddy. I rode my bike into the milkhouse, took off the gloves that I previously couldn&amp;rsquo;t because if they got cold they&amp;rsquo;d never get warm again, and removed my shoe covers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t had any emergency candy, so I ate some candy. Then I left the milkhouse, and walked into the house to get warm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gravel season returns, set your goals</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/gravel-season-returns-set-your-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2022 08:35:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/gravel-season-returns-set-your-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;summers-almost-over&#34;&gt;SUMMER&amp;rsquo;S ALMOST OVER!!!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As August draws to a close, let&amp;rsquo;s all take a moment to remind it that we all hate it and it&amp;rsquo;s a shitty month and it can fuck off. And take February with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;set-your-goals&#34;&gt;Set Your Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, August is almost over and I haven&amp;rsquo;t got out mountain biking nearly as much as I would have liked, but that&amp;rsquo;s okay. A lot of life has been happening, and we deal with it a day at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This spring, you will recall that I finally accomplished my goal of &lt;a href=&#34;../the-windiest-135km-bike-ride/&#34;&gt;doing the 100km+ ride&lt;/a&gt; from our home to my gfs family&amp;rsquo;s farm for Easter. This was my first ride to cross the 100km mark and the conditions were sub-optimal. The windiest day of the year so far as a crosswind definitely didn&amp;rsquo;t make that ride any easier and I was not in the greatest spirits as we crossed the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the obvious thing to do is to create a new, more ambitious goal. So here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Myself and my bicycle, Grimey, will hereby attempt to complete an &amp;ldquo;imperial century&amp;rdquo; ride of 100 miles or more by the end of October of this year. We begin at Buckingham Palace and the Queen herself will drop the green flag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I will be renaming our house Buckingham Palace for the occasion and Ashley will be happy to accept the Queen monicker until the mutinies start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;that-sounds-awful&#34;&gt;That sounds awful&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s funny because we all keep up with our own version of the Joneses. My youtube feed is full of 150 or more mile ultra-endurance races, so doing a ride like this seems quite tame in comparison. But I mention it to normies (aka friends and family) and they are quick to point out that how do you do that it&amp;rsquo;s so far? Same way as you eat an elephant I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;making-a-plan&#34;&gt;Making a plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this ride will be in less than two months, and possibly within a month or so. Which does not leave a heap of time for training and conditioning. Shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll create a more formal plan for myself, but in the meantime, how to prepare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spend more time on the bike. Just in general. Get the body used to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hill training. Head out for less than an hour and repeatedly ride up the biggest hills in the area at full gas, recover on the way back down. It&amp;rsquo;s high-intensity intervals and it sucks but it will build some strength and should hopefully provide quick/substantial cardiovascular gains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Longer, mellow rides. Head out to the rail trails and just cruise for two hours or more. Sometimes go for a second ride that day, make sure the body is okay with having to go when it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really want to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eat and ride. When you&amp;rsquo;re out for extended rides and want to make good time, you need to train your body to expend energy and digest at the same time. So bring a substantial snack to eat at the start of the ride, or even at the halfway point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the last ride, my guts felt gross in the second half from eating the [high-calories == crap] food, so I might need to experiment with this a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stay-tuned&#34;&gt;Stay tuned&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last ride clocked in around 135km and lasted about seven hours, I think? So planning to tack on another hour, which hopefully won&amp;rsquo;t destroy me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone want to loan me a drone and wants to come out for a small section to get some aerial shots, that&amp;rsquo;d be awesome. No pay!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll keep you posted as we move towards R-day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The windiest 135km bike ride</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/the-windiest-135km-bike-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 08:10:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/the-windiest-135km-bike-ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the tale of my longest bike ride to date, a 135km slog through rail trails and dirt roads from our house to the in-lawses place for Easter weekend. There are no particularly high or low points, so please temper your expectations now. Mostly it&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a travelog for myself; making note of what worked, what didn&amp;rsquo;t and where do we go from here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prelude&#34;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pandemic era (early 2020 and ongoing) has been hard on everyone. In early 2021 I burnt out and needed to take over a month away from work to recover. It took months before I was getting back into decent physical and mental condition and I still feel like I&amp;rsquo;m not quite 100%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During that timespan, everyone&amp;rsquo;s horizons seem to have shrunk considerably. Gatherings that used to be common have become anxiety-inducing affairs where everyone needs to weigh the risk of  infection versus benefits of a community. For someone who struggled with gatherings to begin with, the world becomes daunting as we move toward whatever normal will become. So I needed a project where I could focus some energy and would hopefully provide a mental and physical boost even by making the attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just before the start of the pandemic, I picked up a 2019 Devinci Hatchet (57cm frame for a ~6&#39;1&amp;quot; rider, if you care) that had been used as a shop demo, so was able to get quite a deal on it. The bike was quickly named Grimey after a character from &lt;a href=&#34;https://frinkiac.com/episode/S08E23/11661&#34;&gt;the best Simpsons episode ever&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./grimey-profile.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Grimey in profile&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bike really opened up &lt;em&gt;shoulder-season&lt;/em&gt; training for me. Mountain biking is a wonderful pursuit, but the trails aren&amp;rsquo;t open until mid-April and then are crummy again for a good portion of October and November (Canadian monsoon season).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wellness-skrillas&#34;&gt;Wellness Skrillas!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last September I started a contract at my current place of employment that provided an ample boost in &amp;ldquo;Wellness Bucks&amp;rdquo; (not the real name, but way better than the real name). Pondering what sort of crap would be most beneficial to my well-being, obviously &amp;ldquo;new bike shit&amp;rdquo; was the only real thought to cross my mind. So I did some research and pored over bike-gear review sites and picked up a nice jacket, some winter-weight bib tights and some rain-proof booties so I could be out in the rain without my feet being frozen. For anyone who hasn&amp;rsquo;t ridden in the rain with soggy feet, there is no better way to hate cycling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also picked up some seemingly-overpriced-but-amazing-quality bags from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apidura.com&#34;&gt;Apidura&lt;/a&gt;. Along with a couple of water bottle mounts, these allowed me to ditch a backpack and maximize comfort out on the bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;inception&#34;&gt;Inception&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years now I&amp;rsquo;ve been considering making the trek to my partner&amp;rsquo;s Parents&amp;rsquo; place via bicycle. At 125km by car it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;big enough&amp;rdquo; distance without being a &amp;ldquo;ridiculous&amp;rdquo; distance for a pretty green distance rider like myself. I&amp;rsquo;ve done hundreds of 2-hour mountain bike rides, but generally nothing more involved than that, and usually never much more than 10km from the car park.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The confluence of events during the pandemic led me to believe that this might be a decent idea to add a bit of pep-in-my-step and a feather in my cap. To maybe make me start to believe that I can accomplish things and that the world isn&amp;rsquo;t terrifying. Correction: the world is terrifying, but maybe I have the mental fortitude to put up with it, maybe even thrive. So sometime during the winter of 2021-2022, the old cranium slowly focused in on &amp;ldquo;Easter weekend&amp;rdquo; as the time to make the attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;training-plotting&#34;&gt;Training, plotting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much endurance training was actually undertaken during the winter. Like pretty much everyone, I hate training during the winter and indoors. I tried to use the rowing machine over the winter coupled with some weight training using our adjustable dumbbells and a TRX setup. Occasionally I would jump on the spin bike for an hour or so and watch an episode of &lt;em&gt;Call My Agent&lt;/em&gt; while hating it. The biking. &lt;em&gt;Call My Agent&lt;/em&gt; is a good way to brush up on French skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things were able to ramp up a bit in March when the trails were starting to thaw out and were mostly muddy rather than icey. I was able to fire off a nice self-portrait on the first bigger ride of the year with a thick fog covering.. ..well, everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./foggy-ride.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A lone bike rider in the fog with power lines fading into the fog&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there the rides generally got longer and longer, with the exception of hills days. There was only one hills days, but they are really good for increasing cardio capacity (or so I tell myself). I live on the edge of a ridge with some fairly steep sides. It seems like a &lt;a href=&#34;https://nsidc.org/cryosphere/glaciers/gallery/drumlins.html&#34;&gt;drumlin&lt;/a&gt; but I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually looked into that. But there are some decently steep roads in the neighbourhood, so I set out with the sole intention of doing ten hill climbs. Think of high-intensity intervals except where the intervals are defined by going uphill as hard as you can. It only took 40 minutes, but was probably more out of gas than following 2 x 2hr training rides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Training rides were typically pretty gentle since the plan was to go farther than harder. Trying to keep the heart rate around 130-140 bpm (68-74% MHR) and going for about 2 hours at a time, twice a day getting closer to go-time. This roughly correlates with &amp;ldquo;moderate intensity&amp;rdquo; physical activity for anyone keeping track at home. This seemed like a decent &amp;ldquo;could do this all day if necessary&amp;rdquo; pace once you get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lets-talk-jams&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s talk jams&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of time in the saddle staring straight ahead means a lot of time with headphones crammed into my earholes absorbing sounds. [Quick aside: I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to get stuck with out-of-juice wireless headphones, so I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.ca/dp/B00UH35KH8&#34;&gt;some super-good-value wired headphones&lt;/a&gt;]. I don&amp;rsquo;t listen to podcasts because I haven&amp;rsquo;t found any that I don&amp;rsquo;t find boring. My brain is also hypervigilant 74% of the time (100% - [80% of sleeping time]) so it&amp;rsquo;s a nice break to just be able to see some nice countryside and listen to music I&amp;rsquo;ve already heard a billion times. There&amp;rsquo;s a playlist on my phone called &amp;ldquo;grinding&amp;rdquo; and it just gets played on random. Since everyone has different tastes in music, I&amp;rsquo;ll just list out a few of the various things on there. I like having a mix of everything from &amp;ldquo;really mellow/wimpy&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;fast, loud and yelly&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;really-mellowwimpy&#34;&gt;Really Mellow/Wimpy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Juliana Theory:&lt;/strong&gt; Emo band, they have some really good not-super-wimpy songs (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pO_rw83woKc&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I told you this was killing me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) but songs like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jw1KNSuDj1Q&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;August in Bethany&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are just what the doctor ordered when you need to just keep pedalling and feel like you&amp;rsquo;re never going to make it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dashboard Confessional:&lt;/strong&gt; Possibly the whiniest and emoest music out there, it&amp;rsquo;s also fantastic for just zoning out, singing along. I guess when I see it written down it&amp;rsquo;s almost meditative. So that&amp;rsquo;s good, makes the miles tick by. Try &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sxrTzuIc2H8&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Brilliant Dance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;middle-ground&#34;&gt;Middle Ground&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anberlin:&lt;/strong&gt; No idea why this isn&amp;rsquo;t the most popular band in the world. Go listen to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LeVeKammF0s&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stationary Stationery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J2TxQ7oc054&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cold War Transmissions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You probably won&amp;rsquo;t like them, but at least you&amp;rsquo;ll know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saves the Day:&lt;/strong&gt; Poppy emo band. Whiny with a weird hint of teenage angst. I guess &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f5eOwgzJmV0&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shoulder to the Wheel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a good introductory song.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-fast-and-the-yelly&#34;&gt;The fast and the yelly&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These songs are all completely personal. While you&amp;rsquo;re out riding at a comfortable pace, there is no real reason to listen to music like this unless it just makes you feel happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Much the Same:&lt;/strong&gt; A criminally-underrated melodic hardcore (read: punk) band. I recommend the entire album &lt;em&gt;Survive&lt;/em&gt; and if I had to pick a single song, I don&amp;rsquo;t know, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iIykLzlIHNw&#34;&gt;Stitches&lt;/a&gt;. But that&amp;rsquo;s seriously just picking a song more or less randomly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Older &lt;strong&gt;Comeback Kid:&lt;/strong&gt; There were two Comeback Kid albums I really liked, &lt;em&gt;Turn it Around&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Wake the Dead&lt;/em&gt;, with the latter being super good. If you need a quick pick-me-up and don&amp;rsquo;t have any caffeinated anything around, throw on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2NTyyCwwDfY&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wake the Dead&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and problem solved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;variables&#34;&gt;Variables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;April weather in Canada is notoriously shaky, with very mild temperatures and snowstorms roughly equally likely. The week prior to the chosen day, the weather forecast was calling for cool temperatures (high of 6 °C) with chance of rain and it kept alternating between windy/maybe not windy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I am a sucker for a good marketing campaign and have been trained by my outdoorsy overlords to believe that there is &amp;ldquo;no such thing as bad weather, only unsuitable clothing&amp;rdquo;. Which I agree with down to about 2 °C at which point even with woolen socks and state-of-the-art booties, my feet still slowly go numb over a span of a couple of hours and things are a lot less cozy all over. Since that was the expected overnight temperature the night prior to the ride, I was reluctantly still planning to make the attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a &amp;ldquo;special weather statement&amp;rdquo; for the day before my ride, letting us know that there would be strong wind gusts, up to 70 km/h or some such speed. &amp;ldquo;Good&amp;rdquo;, I said to myself, &amp;ldquo;let it blow itself out and leave behind a nice calm day for me!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, doubt had creeped in fairly strongly, as you may infer from my &lt;a href=&#34;https://sadspiders.ca/last-training-ride-before-the-big-ride/&#34;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Part of me still didn&amp;rsquo;t believe I could do it. The catastrophizing came on thick and fast with at least 3 feasible scenarios playing out in my mind, but luckily they all had one thing in common: survivable. So we&amp;rsquo;ll deal with them if we need to, not in brainland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pistols-at-dawn&#34;&gt;Pistols at dawn&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./before-easter-ride.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A protrait of the author minutes before heading out seeking adventure&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day-of dawned cloudy and chilly, with patches of frost dotting the grass. The weather forecast looked pretty bad. Chance of rain in the afternoon and wind kicking up from the southwest, starting at 20 km/h gusting to 40 km/h and picking up steam to 30 km/h gusting to 70 km/h in the afternoon. To put these things in perspective, I like to imagine driving a car at gust speed and putting your hand out the window, palm facing the front to catch the most amount of wind. Shit. 70 km/h is a lot. And I mean, you know what&amp;rsquo;s coming from the damn title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily I headed out just before 8am with the plan to start riding along a rail trail heading west-northwest, so should only be catching a slight headwind. A few snowflakes drifted lazily through the air on my way out of town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./dark-and-stormy.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A Kanses-esque farmscape&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first hint of the suck-assness to come came around 32km in at the 1h45min mark where the trail takes a band to the west-southwest. Which was basically straight into the wind, which is recorded as being about 30km/h sustained at a nearby weather station around that time. That stretch only lasted about half an hour and 8km and it was still early on in the ride, so we sucked it up and kept pedalling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-can-program-my-watch-hows-that-for-nerd-cred&#34;&gt;I can program my watch, how&amp;rsquo;s that for nerd-cred&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With another chunk of wellness-money, I picked up a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.espruino.com/Bangle.js2&#34;&gt;Bangle2js&lt;/a&gt; hackable smartwatch. I haven&amp;rsquo;t put a ton of time into monkeying with it yet, but since I am a doubtful person, I figured that we should add some positive-affirmations to the watch face. I came up with a short list of off-the-cuff statements, fired together about twenty lines of javascript and voila: inspiration. Fun detail: check out the step counter, this photo is from post-ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./watch-face.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hacked watch face&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Good Stuff&amp;rdquo; is probably the lamest of them unfortunately, and I think I got some pep from &amp;ldquo;you can do this!&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;have fun?!&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Keep pedalling&amp;rdquo;. I forgot to add the cyclist classic &amp;ldquo;Shut up legs&amp;rdquo; but, well, I made it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it turns out, &amp;ldquo;just keep pedalling&amp;rdquo; was a great mantra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;open-farmland-for-miles-in-every-direction&#34;&gt;Open farmland for miles in every direction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All shitty things must come to an end, and keep pedalling I did, making a right onto the first of a number of farm roads. The second leg of the journey was a bunch of jibbing and tacking across a grid of dirt roads through open farm country heading primarily to the northwest. The wind, as a reminder, is blowing from the southwest at this point. Which is 90° from my bearing, or directly sideways into me. At 30km/h plus gusts, which are unfortunately not listed in the historical record, but were probably &lt;em&gt;at least&lt;/em&gt; 10km/h higher and probably more. At this point, I am moving forward a bit slower than usual, but &lt;em&gt;I am essentially a small piece of plywood&lt;/em&gt; at the mercy of the winds. This required some actual technical riding skill, which is a far cry from the &amp;ldquo;nice-n-cruzy&amp;rdquo; rides that were the norm during training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture it thusly: you&amp;rsquo;re riding along, leaning into a 30 km/h steady wind coming from directly to your left. The dirt roads have a groove about a foot-and-a-half wide where all of the car (and buggy!) tires have gone, with loose gravel covering the rest of the surface. So you keep the contact points in the middle of this groove, no problem. But now the wind gusts and pushes you into the loose gravel, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you&amp;rsquo;re now required to lean harder into the wind to keep from being completely swept into the ditch. So now you&amp;rsquo;re leaning more and sliding out in the loose gravel and cursing your idiot self for not just pulling the phone out of your back pocket and calling for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can&amp;rsquo;t. Because you can do this, at this point you &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to do this. For no reason other than that you&amp;rsquo;ve started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this went on for about 25km, interspersed at the end of every segment with a few minutes of heading northeast for a few hundred meters until the next side road. And those few minutes are &lt;strong&gt;glorious&lt;/strong&gt; and keep morale from flat-lining. With this strong, gusty wind firmly at my back, I watch my heart rate fall into the &amp;ldquo;reasonable&amp;rdquo; zone while maintaining 35 km/h with minimal effort and absolutely no headwind. It&amp;rsquo;s an amazing feeling, but so fleeting. Also at one point I passed a mennonite church in-session and waved at all the horses in their little coats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./horses.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Mennonites cars parked out front, all mustangs&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This segment ends in a small town, where a pit stop at the local donuttery provides a sugar boost and a top-up for the water bottles. This also marked roughly the halfway point of the trip, and it&amp;rsquo;s now as easy to continue as to head back. I also knew that there was a fairly lengthy section coming up soon heading mostly north which should provide a nice tailwind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-send&#34;&gt;Full Send&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few more back roads and &lt;em&gt;gasp&lt;/em&gt; some tarmac sections and we were onto what would probably be the start of some high-speed awesomeness to make up for the &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to fall at any second&amp;rdquo; feelings I&amp;rsquo;d been plagued with for the past two hours. Which is a long time to expect to fall at any moment, and less fun than it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we get to the road pointing north, and it&amp;rsquo;s as great as expected. Minimal effort, even to climb hills, maintaining 30 km/h while still having a comparative rest. Finally that feeling of &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to make it!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is short-lived, of course. After twenty minutes, there are rocks blocking the road and signs saying this is private property and not to trespass. So I sit at the intersection with a stupid look on my face for a minute, then pull out my phone to figure out wtf. The next nearest roads travelling my direction will require some serious detouring, with at least part of that ride directly into the wind. Fuck it, says I, these signs must not take my particular conundrum into account. And I push on over the rocks, to grandmother&amp;rsquo;s house we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dirt lane is clearly someone&amp;rsquo;s muddin&amp;rsquo; lane. Pondlike-puddles dot the route and even with a tailwind the going is slow and off-roading is required to keep from getting my nice booties coated in mud. Further along, a forest, complete with a number of blown-down trees. Surprisingly, they fell when the wind was coming from the opposite direction and thus were not casualties of today. However, it is a reminder of the vague danger of falling trees along forested trails on windy days. I&amp;rsquo;m wearing a helmet, I&amp;rsquo;ll be fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./trees-down.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Several trees fallen across a section of dirt road&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So after climbing over the trees and making my way a bit further along the dirt path, I make a nice discovery: I&amp;rsquo;ve been here before! I&amp;rsquo;ve made shorter rides along these routes in the past, and this is where I made my northward turn. I can do it, I&amp;rsquo;ve ridden from here before!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trail opened up again, but the wind seems to have shifted slightly so it&amp;rsquo;s now coming somewhat from my lefthand side. It&amp;rsquo;s about a moot point, not really helping but not really slowing me down either. I can live with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-down-one-to-go&#34;&gt;Three down, one to go&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last leg of the trip is a northwesterly jaunt along an old rail trail. Over 100km down and a little more than 30km to go. At this point though, the Clif bars and RealFruit gummies and bottle of Coke and fig bars and Mars bars are catching up with my poor stomach. I keep on eating something every half hour or forty-five minutes so I don&amp;rsquo;t get the dreaded &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bikeradar.com/advice/fitness-and-training/how-to-avoid-bonking-on-a-bike-ride/&#34;&gt;bonk&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;ldquo;that sudden, catastrophic loss of energy&amp;rdquo;). I&amp;rsquo;m definitely getting tired at this point, I noted that I was starting to feel tired at the 85km mark. Which is fine, I expected tired. So long as I can keep my energy levels up, I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t get that shakey &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to cry because I&amp;rsquo;m so tired&amp;rdquo; feeling. If you&amp;rsquo;ve had the feeling you know how desperately you want to avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting onto the rail trail was a little bit of a morale hit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./railtrail-start.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Some snow to the side of a poorly-maintained rail trail&#34;&gt;
[Image caption: &amp;ldquo;Fuck.&amp;rdquo;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the big version of the photo, you can see the odometer at 104km, and also a pile of snow still sitting at the side of a very gravelly trail. These trails are heavily travelled by ATVs and side-by-sides, all of whom think it is &amp;ldquo;rad&amp;rdquo; to chew up the trail until it is a washboardy mess. Flashbacks to the gravel road with the perfect crosswind and the relentless threat of being laying down a moment from now. By my clock I began this section at about 13:30, or 1:30pm for those of us who hate things being unambiguous. The historical record for a nearby weather station puts this entire last section at sustained winds of around 40km/h, and I know from looking at the conditions from the day-of that there were recorded gusts over 70km/h. From exactly at my left side. But well, I&amp;rsquo;ve made it this far dammit. You just have to stuff down all the doubts and the fatigue and just keep pedalling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily the washboard-gravel section only last for a few kilometers before giving way to a nicely maintained trail for the remainder of the trip. This made the relentless and gusting wind a bit more bearable, but this was definitely the part of the trip that was nothing but an unenjoyable slog. &amp;ldquo;I just want to get there, and lay down face down in the grass until I feel less like shit&amp;rdquo;. Still not bonking, which is great, but the extra effort to counteract the wind and the fact that I was using an unexpectedly large amount of upper-body movements to stay upright has taken its toll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-solid-slap-in-the-face&#34;&gt;A solid slap in the face&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I got close to the destination, I knew there was a section about 3km long that would bring me from the trail, along a section of tarmac, to the destination. Honestly a pretty perfect set-up. So I got out on the tarmac, went into the drops (hands on bottom part of curly handlebars) and started gently cruising to the finish line. Until the forested section ended and I was suddenly in the middle of a violent windstorm which simultaneously almost brought me to a stop and blew me off the road. Not quite an exact headwind, just enough coming from the side to keep me off-balance for the final fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was almost poetic, once I was able to catch my breath and think about it. When you&amp;rsquo;re on easy street, you&amp;rsquo;ve started celebrating too soon and suddenly have to revert back to survival mode for one last spell. It took a lot to get through the last stretch. I stopped at the first intersection along that road and tried to decide if this is where I call an end to my journey, to ask for help to get the last 2km down the road. Even at rest the wind almost knocked me over. But again, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t. My legs could still push against the pedals, so I threw my leg over the saddle, pushed my doubts aside and inched my way along that road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;welcoming-committee&#34;&gt;Welcoming Committee&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming down that road at a glacial 10 km/h, tucked low on the drops and riding in the wrong lane to try to take advantage of the wind being launched over the road by the ditch, my girlfriend and her family had all come out the lane to celebrate this awful victory. I think I was semi-successful at pretending I was really happy to see everybody, but in that moment I just wanted to ride my bike behind the barn, lie face down and let out all the frustrations that had been building for the last six hours in a good solid cry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./arrival.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Blown off the driveway&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Image caption: Literally blown off the driveway. A slog right to the finish line.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really do appreciate them coming out, but.. ..emotions are hard. After-the-fact I really wish I could have jumped up and down and cracked a beer right away and celebrated. But I just wasn&amp;rsquo;t there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never did have that cry. The bike was laid down on its side and I just sat on the side of a hill with Ashley and her brother Scott while I tried to regain my composure. I laid down on my back for a bit, but suddenly got very dizzy and had to sit back up with my head between my knees. It passed and I was slowly able to come back to life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./denouement.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Forcing a smile&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;epilogue&#34;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clock was started at 7:52am and the recorded distance was a touch over 135km. Moving time 6h44m with total elapsed time 7h20m. Average speed was a respectable 20.1 km/h.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure this whole trip would have been a lot less exciting and dramatic without the wind, but it definitely has turned this into a better story. I shit you not when I say this was a ridiculously windy day, here&amp;rsquo;s a graphic I stole from &lt;em&gt;El Weather Netwerko&lt;/em&gt; to sum up the day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./weathernetwork.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Weather network showing 90+km/h gusts the day of the ride&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My ride took place in the general area of where the graphic for Hamilton is covering and into the red patch above it. So if anything I could possibly be &lt;em&gt;understating&lt;/em&gt; the wind speed that day. Oh my.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right after the ride we hung out and had a couple of beers and then some water. Aside from some slight exhaustion it was difficult to take a deep breath for a while, I wonder if the cold air irritated my lungs. The temperature maxxed out at 10 °C that day and was colder for much of the ride. The posture of being on a bike for that long isn&amp;rsquo;t particularly good when you aren&amp;rsquo;t adapted for it, and my wrists and deltoid muscles did some minor throbbing the rest of the day, but never enough to bother with taking any pain relievers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a couple of drinks, I fell asleep for an hour or so, and my stomach still had that gut-rot feeling and I ended up eating a pretty minimal dinner that night. Woke up for a bit and &amp;ldquo;just hung out&amp;rdquo;, then back to bed around normal time, for a disappointingly-average sleep. However, I am known to wake up into panic attacks on occasion (it&amp;rsquo;s as fun as it sounds) and had considered that it might happen considering the unknowns that had been dealt with that day. I can happily report that I woke up once in the night, calmly, and fell back asleep after somehow suppressing needing to take a whiz and not wanting to get up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day I went for an easy 40-minute recovery ride in the relatively-so-calm local roads while listening to the album &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x2iGiFxr6D8&#34;&gt;Goodbye&lt;/a&gt; by Aurora Borealis. I definitely felt drained, but it was nice to get things moving since my knees were a bit sore on waking, along with a bit of soreness in my quads mostly, maybe a bit of glutes and hammies. Made me wonder what the experience would have been like in non-stupid conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Easter lunch was possibly the greatest meal ever eaten. With a settled stomach and a backlog of calories to replenish, it&amp;rsquo;s like the taste of everything was enhanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Und das, as they say, is alles. The bike came home on a rack. I marvelled at how easy and fast driving is. Perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Last training ride before the big ride</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/last-training-ride-before-the-big-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2022 13:36:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/last-training-ride-before-the-big-ride/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;thoughts-on-leaving-the-comfort-of-zone&#34;&gt;Thoughts on leaving the comfort of zone.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s ride was a nice, gentle, three hour long and 60km trek. Headed away from home for an hour and a half before turning tail and heading along the same path back. The main goal was to make sure to stay well fuelled, to remember to get some sort of snack down the hatch every half hour and make sure the old digestive tract was happy enough with this arrangement. I&amp;rsquo;m encouraged to anonouce that indeed this was the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temperature hovered around 3°C (who cares how many Fs, learn metric plz) for the duration, which prompted a switch to heavier lobster-gloves around the halfway mark, but then required switching back to the lightweight gloves most of the way back. It also made the granola bars and whatnot quite difficult to maow through, a little more crunchy than we&amp;rsquo;re used to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;neat&#34;&gt;Neat&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next Friday is a 135km ride from &lt;em&gt;[redacted]&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;[redacted]&lt;/em&gt; for the Easter weekend. Along rail trails and gravel roads and minimal tarmac. Cars scare the hell out of me because they are x thousand-pound missiles with idiots at the helm. A pretty cynical view but not entirely inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you realize that by definition half the people out there have IQs of less than a hundred?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s daunting, I am finding the whole thing fairly intimidating. I&amp;rsquo;ve never really spent more than four-and-a-half straight hours on a bike. So to add another half that again seems like a lot. With an anxious mind, this is a treasure-trove. Will my butt get numb and super uncomfortable? What if I bonk and feel like death at the &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; hour mark? What if my wrists and shoulders get super sore? What if I just &lt;em&gt;can&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And since you&amp;rsquo;re not going to ask, I&amp;rsquo;ll answer anyways: I bring a small amount of emergency toilet papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess the answer is always just &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rsquo;ll deal with it&amp;rdquo;, which is true but also hard to accept. And this is how I am leaving my comfort zone. To trust that things will be fine, and if they aren&amp;rsquo;t, we&amp;rsquo;ll solve problems as they arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So.. ..let&amp;rsquo;s get on it with it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Cup Downhill 2022 starts next weekend!</title>
      <link>https://sadspiders.ca/world-cup-downhill-2022-starts-next-weekend/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 16:29:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sadspiders.ca/world-cup-downhill-2022-starts-next-weekend/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;code-orange-all-hands-on-deck&#34;&gt;Code Orange; All hands on deck.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;World Cup Downhill racing starts again for the 2022 season this weekend! And yes, you should absolutely watch it. Look, the good nerds over at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redbull.com/int-en/need-to-know-lourdes-uci-mtb-world-cup-preview&#34;&gt;Red Bull&lt;/a&gt; have thrown together a cheat sheet so that you can ignore everything I am about to say and just go there! No wait, do not go to a different website. This is your home now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only race day is a good time, the entire week before the race has daily updates from various athletes and teams released via [&lt;em&gt;popular streaming service&lt;/em&gt;]. If you want to get involved properly, here&amp;rsquo;s a breakdown of some of the best stuff to watch before [&lt;em&gt;streaming service&lt;/em&gt;] learns your preferences and feeds you nothing but this and also weird conspiracy videos because you watched one as a joke once. The only real &amp;ldquo;conspiracy&amp;rdquo; is that Birds aren&amp;rsquo;t Real. Look into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sport attracts a fun array of people. You might think that they are all screw-loose low-IQ weirdos but you would only be one-third right; most of them seem to be of average IQ or higher and generally pretty normal. Getting to know the riders goes a long way in the enjoyment because there will always be people you want to win and people you want to lose. But you have to pretend to be sportsmanlike and just say things like &amp;ldquo;I just want him to win less&amp;rdquo; but it&amp;rsquo;s okay we all do that and know what you mean (&amp;ldquo;fuck that guy&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;track-walk&#34;&gt;Track Walk&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before being allowed to ride down the track, all athletes participate in a track walk. This allows them to hang out with one another, tell stories, and if it&amp;rsquo;s been raining they will slip and fall a few times each. I know this because New Zealand native Wyn Masters posts his usually-pretty-good &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iQSVBatQqQY&#34;&gt;WynTV track walks&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: link is from the last time the race was in Lourdes back in 2017).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a great way to learn the players in the game. Wyn is a master interviewer in that he just says whatever he thinks without thinking about it so you learn some fun stuff from everyone. He also seems to be pretty universally liked so everyone is open with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Track walks are also where you can learn which parts of the course riders are excited for and which are dreaded which helps to understand what they&amp;rsquo;re going through come race day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice-videos&#34;&gt;Practice videos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire time after track walk until race day, the good folks down at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vitalmtb.com/&#34;&gt;Vital MTB&lt;/a&gt; release daily footage of what has been happening. These offer good insight into how riders progress from a first attempt at a difficult section to really having it nailed down. There are also usually a fair number of entertaining crashes and occasionally some gnarly/scary-looking crashes. Along with these videos, riders will post their point-of-view footage from practice so you get a vague sense of what things will be like from their perspective. I have a feeling this might actually be better with in virtual reality, since current footage is notoriously bad at conveying how steep things actually are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course I would be remiss not to mention &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pinkbike.com&#34;&gt;Pinkbike&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s coverage in this discussion. They were recently acquired by Outside Media or something and the whole comments section hates them for it, but the comments section is also just notoriously bitchy about everything (e.g. &amp;ldquo;pick a tire size and be a dick about it&amp;rdquo;). Oh yeah, but I was going to say that Pinkbike is also where a lot of these videos are aggregated, so a daily visit to their site for the week before a race will keep you up-to-date on the haps. Also be sure to read the comments because there are a lot of gems scattered in there. Actually, as much as possible, just read the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;qualies-qualifying&#34;&gt;Qualies (Qualifying)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day before the race (sometimes two days before) there is a qualifying heat to determine the order everyone will come down the mountain. Red Bull always tries to do this thing where they talk to everyone as soon as their run is done and they are exhausted and can&amp;rsquo;t formulate a decent thought/sentence and it generally sucks shit. It is considered wise to assume that the outcome of qualifying will be almost exactly the same as the outcome of the race because some people do that and others are sarcastic jerks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;race-day-omfg-&#34;&gt;RACE DAY OMFG 🚴💨&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of these races are held in Europe. This weekend, for example, takes places in Lourdes in the French Pyrenees. Neat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The women race first and are definitely entertaining enough to watch. Over the last few years the competition has really upped their game and to win the race they need to hit all the jumps the men do. The &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redbull.com/int-en/events/uci-mountain-bike-world-cup-lourdes&#34;&gt;Red Bull World Cup Downhill brought to you by Mercedez-Benz&lt;/a&gt; (seriously) livestream starts at 6:25am in my part of North America, which means I get to wake up, put on some coffee and spend half my day just relaxing and enjoying some biking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The men&amp;rsquo;s broadbast starts some time around 9:30 or 10 am, about half an hour after the ladies finish and goes for a good while. It usually gets really exciting once the last twenty or so dudes start making their way down. A lot of them are buddies so you&amp;rsquo;ll see some good sportsmanship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;rob-warner&#34;&gt;Rob Warner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the announcers is named Rob Warner and even if you don&amp;rsquo;t know what&amp;rsquo;s going on, make sure you have the volume turned up because you&amp;rsquo;ll get really excited just because he gets so damn excited. Seriously, he&amp;rsquo;s about 25-30% of the reason I watch at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;people-to-gun-for&#34;&gt;People to gun for&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, you&amp;rsquo;re new and that&amp;rsquo;s okay. Here&amp;rsquo;s a cheatsheet on some people I like off the top of my head and why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;ladies&#34;&gt;Ladies&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cammy Balanche:&lt;/strong&gt; She all of a sudden got really good a couple of years ago and is now always near the top. If I could go for a beer with any of the ladies, it would be her.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rachel Atherton:&lt;/strong&gt; Fresh off the birth of her first child last year, she&amp;rsquo;s been on top of the game for ages and it will be interesting to see if she can maintain it. I say yes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Myriam Nicole:&lt;/strong&gt; She&amp;rsquo;s french so there&amp;rsquo;s like 50% chance of her winning any given race.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;gentlemen&#34;&gt;Gentlemen&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Greg Minaar:&lt;/strong&gt; He&amp;rsquo;s like as old as me and still near the top of his game. Ladies think he&amp;rsquo;s handsome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Troy Brosnan:&lt;/strong&gt; He reminds me a lot of the New Zealand kid Duncan from Bob&amp;rsquo;s Burgers for some reason. But he&amp;rsquo;s Mr. Consistent in that he places like second or third or 50th in every race and I really want to see him win more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finn Iles:&lt;/strong&gt; Him and Mark Wallace are Canada&amp;rsquo;s top dudes and so that&amp;rsquo;s always fun to watch. He&amp;rsquo;s young so he used to crash a lot so hopefully this year he&amp;rsquo;ll be the perfect mix of zesty and italian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reece Wilson:&lt;/strong&gt; He&amp;rsquo;s this young gun who came out of nowhere and is super good. Last year he probably had the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kh15vDDwRGE&#34;&gt;funnest/craziest crash of the whole season&lt;/a&gt; and walked away from it. He also does some announcing and has a fun Scottish accent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gee Atherton:&lt;/strong&gt; In reality, Gee doesn&amp;rsquo;t have much of a chance of winning. The big brother of Rachel (see above), he&amp;rsquo;s had his fair share of the spotlight over the years. If you want to watch a really scary crash video, he went over the bars on a very exposed ridge called the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_hRrA3_MvQ8&#34;&gt;Knife Edge&lt;/a&gt; and ended up spending some time in the hospital and a lot of time doing physical therapy. I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure he&amp;rsquo;s back racing this year, just to be back out there would be a huge accomplishment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of others I could thrown in but they&amp;rsquo;re all just &amp;ldquo;they seem like a good dude/dudette and it would be nice if they won.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;yessss&#34;&gt;Yessss&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should now have a good starting point for getting into watching professional downhill mountain bike racing. I&amp;rsquo;m also excited because we&amp;rsquo;re planning on going to the race at Mont Ste Anne in Québec this year, so if you have any interest in going, starting to watch now is a good starting point to full enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>